<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon the Antisynodalia americana, a treatise printed in old England; in the name of the dissenting brethren in the synod held at Boston in New England 1662. Tending to clear the elders and churches of New England from those evils and declinings charged upon many of them in the two prefaces before the said book. Together with an answer unto the reasons alledged for the opinion of the dissenters, and a reply to such answers as are given to the arguments of the synod. / by John Allin, pastor of the Church of Christ at Dedham in N. England.</title>
            <author>Allin, John, 1596-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08272</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80921648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W19760</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80921648</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 80921648</idno>
            <idno type="VID">191784</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191784)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2887:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon the Antisynodalia americana, a treatise printed in old England; in the name of the dissenting brethren in the synod held at Boston in New England 1662. Tending to clear the elders and churches of New England from those evils and declinings charged upon many of them in the two prefaces before the said book. Together with an answer unto the reasons alledged for the opinion of the dissenters, and a reply to such answers as are given to the arguments of the synod. / by John Allin, pastor of the Church of Christ at Dedham in N. England.</title>
                  <author>Allin, John, 1596-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.G. and M.J. for Hezekiah Usher of Boston.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Boston Public Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chauncy, Charles, 1592-1672. --  Anti-synodalia scripta americana.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:191784:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANIMADVERSIONS UPON THE <hi>ANTISYNODALIA AMERICANA,</hi> A TREATISE Printed in <hi>Old England,</hi> In the Name of the DISSENTING BRETHREN In the SYNOD held at <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>New England</hi> 1662.</p>
            <p>Tending to Clear the ELDERS and CHURCHES of <hi>New England</hi> from thoſe Evils and Declinings charged upon many of them in the two Prefaces before the ſaid Book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with</hi> AN ANSVVER UNTO The Reaſons alledged for the Opinion of the Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>And a REPLY to ſuch Anſwers as are given to the Arguments of the SYNOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN ALLIN, <hi>Paſtor of the Church of Chriſt at</hi> Dedham <hi>in</hi> N. England.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 3.1, 2.</hi>
               </bibl> What advantage then hath the Jew? or what profit is there of Circumciſion? Much every way: chiefly, becauſe that unto them were committed the Oracles of God.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 3.27, 28.</hi>
               </bibl> For as many of you as have been baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt. There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither Bond nor Free, there is neither Male nor Female, for ye are all one in Chriſt Jeſus.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 12.15, 16.</hi>
               </bibl> Looking diligently, leſt any man fail of the grace of God, left any root of bitterneſs ſpringing up, trouble you, and thereby many be defiled. Leſt there be any fornicator, or profane perſon, as <hi>Eſau,</hi> who for a morſel of meat ſold his Birthright.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Cambridge:</hi> Printed by <hi>S.G.</hi> and <hi>M. J.</hi> for <hi>Hezekiah <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> of <hi>Boſton.</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:191784:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:191784:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ch is the Infirmity and Corruption of Man, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Subtilty of Satan the Enemy of Truth, Purity, and Peace, and the holy and juſt Dispenſation of God Permitting and Ordering all things to his moſt glorious Ends; that frequent Experience ſheweth how hard it is for a People deſirous to walk in all the wayes of God, to ſteer a right courſe between the Gulf of Profaning the Ordinances by an over-looſe Diſpenſation thereof, on the one hand; and the Rocks of Rigid Separation, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſm, and the like, on the other hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And hence it may ſeem the leſs ſtrange, that (notwithſtanding the Eminent Lights we have had, holding forth</hi> The Covenant-intereſt of the Church-ſeed, <hi>and</hi> The Duty of Churches to improve the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances for their good) <hi>yet the Practice hereof hath not obtained in many of our Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That this Caſe is now become matter of publick Dispute between the late</hi> Synod, <hi>and ſome</hi> Diſſenting Brethren; <hi>though it be cauſe of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, yet we deſire herein to ſubmit to the onely wiſe God, hoping and waiting upon Him to ſee the Improvement thereof for good, and for the further clearing up unto us what is</hi> His good, perfect, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Will <hi>in this caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When theſe</hi> Antiſynodalia <hi>of our Brethren came to our hands, and</hi> Another Eſſay <hi>of the ſame nature was here Publiſhed, ſome godly and wiſe Chriſtians adviſed the</hi> Elders <hi>to let them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſs in ſilence; conceiving that they would not ſo take with the People, as to hinder the Practice of</hi> the Doctrine of the Synod: <hi>and that a</hi> Reply <hi>would occaſion fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſputes and Conteſts. But, upon ſerious conſideration of the matter by divers</hi> Elders <hi>met to that End, the</hi> Reaſons <hi>on the other ſide did preponderate. Such as theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:191784:3"/> 1. We being perſwaded of the Doctrine of the Synod, and not finding any Weight in thoſe Tractates to change our Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it ſeemed to us, that by ſilence we ſhould be ſinfully want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Truth of God, (a preſent Truth that many godly ones are enquiring into) and to the Juſt Intereſt of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Truth being aſſerted in ſo Solemn an Ordinance, <hi>viz.</hi> The Aſſembly of the Elders, and other Meſſengers of ſo many Churches, after ſolemn ſeeking the Face of God, and much ſearch into the Scriptures, with large Diſputes about the ſame; Our ſilence in this caſe would not onely render that Ordinance uſeleſs and vain at preſent, but alſo diſcourage the Churches in after-times to make uſe thereof for their neceſſary Eſtabliſhment in Truth and Peace.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We ſee evidently, that the Principles of our Diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren give great Advantages to the <hi>Antipoedobaptiſts,</hi> which if we be ſilent, will tend much to their Encouragement and Encreaſe, to the Hazard of our Churches.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Theſe Treatiſes coming into the Peoples hands, if no Anſwer ſhould be returned, will much ſtrengthen the hands of ſuch as are Diſſenters, and diſcourage the hearts of others from the Practice of the Doctrine of the Synod, for the good of Poſterity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thoſe unjuſt Aſperſions caſt upon many of the Elders and Churches of <hi>New-England</hi> in the two Prefaces to the <hi>Antiſynoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> do tend much to weaken the Authority of their Miniſtry and Diſpenſations, and would lay them under much Scandal in <hi>Old-England</hi> and <hi>New,</hi> ſhould not a juſt Apologie and Anſwer be made thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For theſe and the like Reaſons, it was thought neceſſary to return a juſt Anſwer to theſe Books, publiſhed in Oppoſition to</hi> the Doctrine of the Synod. <hi>But that my Brethren ſhould have any eye upon my ſelf to undertake this part of the Work;</hi> viz. <hi>To Examine, and make Reply to theſe</hi> Antiſynodalia, <hi>was very farre from my thoughts. Yet when I could by no Perſwaſions and Intreaties prevail with them, to
<pb facs="tcp:191784:3"/>Call out ſome other more able for this Work (whereof we had choyce) I conſidered, that</hi> the Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets, <hi>and that the Lord is not wont to deny Aſſiſtance to ſuch as he calleth forth to any Service; yea, that He delighteth to</hi> ſhew His ſtrength in weakneſs: <hi>In hope hereof, I have by his Grace and Help run through theſe</hi> Antiſynodalia, <hi>in my plain and homely manner (loving alwayes to speak to vulgar Capacities) wiſhing heartily it had been done by ſome better hand, that might have performed it more throughly. This onely I have to ſay for my ſelf, That I have not willingly declined any ſeeming ſtrength of Reaſon, nor ſought by Shifts and Evaſions to darken any ſeeming Light of Truth held forth in theſe</hi> Antiſynodalia; <hi>but have Candidly (according to my meaſure)</hi> Searched the Scripture whether thoſe things were ſo. <hi>As I have believed, ſo have I ſpoken: As I finde in the</hi> Law and Teſtimony, <hi>ſo have I written. What weakneſſes and defects may be diſcovered by a more judicious Eye, I hope (through Grace) I ſhall be willing to ſee and reform upon intimation thereof; onely let no Truth herein held forth, be the leſs eſteemed for the Infirmity of the Inſtrument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall commit this Caſe of the</hi> Church-ſeed <hi>unto that God, who of his rich Grace hath undertaken to be their God; Beſeeching Him to make his Wayes plain before the face of his People, and to improve theſe Diſputes to common Edification, according to the good pleaſure of his will.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, <hi>JOHN ALLIN.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>From my Study in <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>N.E.</hi> 
                  <date>6 day, 11 mon. 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:191784:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191784:4"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS UPON THE <hi>ANTISYNODALIA AMERICANA.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Being Animadverſions upon the two</hi> Prefaces: <hi>The firſt,</hi> To the Reader; <hi>the ſecond,</hi> To the Honoured General Court.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no good ſign, that the Publiſher of theſe <hi>Anti-Synodalia</hi> doth ſo foully ſtumble at the Threſhold, in his firſt ſtepping forth into this Buſineſs. For where as he pretendeth, <q>
                     <hi>As a Lover of the Truth, to Publiſh this Treatiſe without any Commiſſion from the Diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which he deſireth them not to be offended with:</hi>
                  </q> and affirms it as a truth, <q>
                     <hi>That the perſons engaged in this Diſſent, had much rather this Treatiſe were ſuppreſſed, and as an untimely birth to have been buried in everlaſting darkneſs.</hi>
                  </q> The contrary hereunto is evidently evinced by the whole Preface following; which ſpeaketh no more in the perſon of the Publiſher, but of the Diſſenters: and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they endeavour to Anſwer four Objections againſt the Publiſhing thereof. And in Anſwer to the firſt Objection, taken from the <hi>Ill conſequences that might follow,</hi> they declare a Reſolution to have it Publiſhed, whatever ſhould follow; concluding in the words of <hi>Eſther, If I periſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, I periſh.</hi> Beſides, it is well known here, how
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191784:5"/>earneſt and reſolute one of the chief of them was to have it Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Objections here mentioned: The three firſt, from <hi>The ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a Conſequences that may follow; The trouble of the Peace of the Churches hereby;</hi> and from <hi>The Novelty of their Opinion;</hi> I know not of any that made theſe Objections: Surely that language was not heard in the Synod, but their own Reaſon might object ſuch things. The fourth Objection is, A pretended <hi>Concurrence of all other Congregational Churches they know of, to countenance their Cauſe,</hi> but without any ſufficient Proof thereof. But ſeeing it is now Publiſhed, though <hi>unſ aſonably,</hi> (as is confeſſed) I ſhall not trouble my ſelf and the Reader about the Anſwers to the <hi>Objections,</hi> but apply my ſelf to wipe off thoſe uncharitable and unjuſt Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that in this Preface are caſt upon many of the Elders and Churches of <hi>New-England.</hi> Wherein (that I may not wrong any of our beloved Brethren, the Diſſenters) I muſt ſay this on their behalf, That ſome of them do profeſs that they had no hand in this firſt Preface, nor in the Publiſhing thereof, nor any knowledge thereof: And I have reaſon to think ſo of others of them, who I hope have other thoughts of their Brethren, then this Preface hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth. So that ſo farre as I conceive, it is the act of one of them onely, or chiefly.</p>
               <p>I take notice of Seven Imputations caſt upon us, which I ſhall ſpeak unto.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Author of this Preface complaineth of <q>
                     <hi>The courſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of their Tenent, both in the Synod, and in the General Court, where they expected more Patrons then did appear.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That none may hence judge otherwiſe then the truth is; In reſpect of the Synod, it cannot be denied that the matter in queſtion was placidly, fully, and oft-over Debated, all their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments weighed, all Writings preſented were read, conſidered, and ſome publickly anſwered: So that all the <hi>courſe Entertainment</hi> was, that their Tenent was not embraced by the Synod. And as for the Honoured General Court, if they were ſo farre ſatisfied with the Anſwers of the Synod to that Queſtion about <hi>The Subject of Baptiſm</hi> propounded by them, that they did not think fit in their Wiſdome
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:191784:5"/>to countenance and encourage a Party riſing up in Oppoſition thereto, as tending to Diviſions and Diſturbances amongſt us; they may thank themſelves for ſuch <hi>courſe Entertainment,</hi> if they will ſo account of it.</p>
               <p>But to aggravate this <hi>courſe Entertainment,</hi> he addeth, <q>
                     <hi>Though it be no other Doctrine then of all the Congregational Churches in</hi> Holland, England, Ireland, <hi>and</hi> New-England, <hi>and alſo in</hi> New-Haven, <hi>and</hi> Plimouth <hi>Juriſdictions; yea, and alſo that it hath been the Judgement and general Practice of the Churches in the</hi> Bay, <hi>ſome few inconſiderable excepted, for thirty years.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here is a great Pretence of <hi>general Concurrence</hi> with their Tenent, but without Proof, and beyond the truth. And to make the Number ſeem the greater, beſides <hi>New-England,</hi> he addeth, <hi>And alſo</hi> New-Haven, Plimouth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if theſe were not <hi>New-England</hi> Churches. As for thoſe Forreign Churches, it doth not appear whether as yet (many of them at leaſt) have declared their Judgement in this caſe. Yea, I have heard from one of good note, that knows many of thoſe Churches, who upon the queſtion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>That this caſe hath not as yet been conſidered in many of thoſe Churches.</hi> And if their Practice have not yet ſuited to the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Synod,</hi> we know by our own experience how many hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances there may be of that, though their Judgement be for it. But concerning the Judgement of <hi>New-England</hi> Elders and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, let the Preface to the Synod be read, by which it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, That the moſt Eminent Elders in the moſt conſiderable Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the Meſſengers of the Churches of <hi>New-England,</hi> were generally for this Doctrine in the Synod held at <hi>Cambridge</hi> in the year 1648. I ſhall mention onely that Paſſage of famous <hi>Hooker, whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpel in all the Churches,</hi> and who might know as much of the Principles of the Congregational Churches as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: <hi>It is not the queſtion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Whether wicked Members, while they are ſinfully tolerated in the Church, they and their ſeed may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of Priviledges; for this is beyond queſtion: nor do I know, or ever heard it denied by any of ours.</hi> Survey, Part 3. Chap. 2. pag. 11. Whereby it doth appear, that he took it for a general Confeſſion on all hands, That it is the Intereſt in the Outward Covenant that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191784:6"/>giveth right to Outward Priviledges of the Church; which is the Foundation of the Doctrine of the Synod. Whereas the Tenent of our Diſſenting Brethren is, <hi>That Members of the Church admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in minority, and having the Covenant ſealed by Baptiſm, if being adult, they hold not forth ſaving Faith and Repentance to the judgement of the Church, even ſo as to come into full Communion; neither they nor their ſeed may partake of Priviledges, they are</hi> Felones de ſe, <hi>Self-m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtherers, Diſcovenanted of God, and are not ſo much as Foederally holy, ſo ſoon as they be out of their Non-age;</hi> as will appear after: which Tenent I cannot believe will be owned by moſt of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches named, if by any of them.</p>
               <p>This Author addeth further, <q>
                     <hi>That yet now this Tenent is laden with Reproaches of Antichriſtianiſm and Anabaptiſm.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> If an Argument or two were uſed in the Synod, taken from ſuch Conſequences, is this ground enough to ſay <hi>it is laden with ſuch Reproaches?</hi> (and other ground I know none.) Yet for that of <hi>Anabaptiſm,</hi> it will appear the Principles of the Diſſenters are ſo near a Kin, if not the ſame with theirs, that we cannot but fear a great tendency thereunto: and what encouragement they take from thence, we are very ſenſible.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In anſwering the firſt Objection, this Prefacer takes occaſion, upon ſuppoſition of the Doctrine of the Synod, to charge <q>
                     <hi>the Bay Churches with a ſin which he cannot ſee how it can ſtand with peace of Conſcience, in leaving their former practice in diſpenſing the Seals, and taking up a new manner thereof; yea a grievous ſin, in depriving ſo many Infants of Baptiſm for thirty years; yea, of the ſame nature, and ſomewhat worſe then that of the Phar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſees,</hi> Luke 7.29, 30. <hi>diſannulling the counſel of God againſt themſelves, and ſo many hundred poor Infants whom the Kingdome of God (as we now plead) belongs unto: and a practical Anabaptiſm.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is indeed a grief of heart to many Elders and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that the practice of the Rule, according to the Doctrine of the late Synod, cannot yet obtain in their Churches; but they are not convinced <hi>it is a ſin in them that cannot ſtand with peace of Conſcience,</hi> as the caſe ſtandeth: becauſe <hi>all things</hi> in the Church <hi>must be done to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fication;</hi> which in this caſe cannot be put in practice, eſpecially
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:191784:6"/>in reference to the fifth Propoſition, with peace and edification, by reaſon of the ſtrong oppoſition made by theſe, and other like Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters When this matter was under Conſideration in the Synod 1648. the Author of this Preface knoweth well who it was that profeſſed. <hi>He would oppoſe it with all his might:</hi> by reaſon whereof, and the Diſſent of ſome few more it was laid aſide at that time. It ſeemeth to me very hard dealing, for Brethren ſo ſtrongly to oppoſe others in doing their Duty, and then to charge them with <hi>a ſin that cannot ſtand with peace of Conſcience</hi> if they do it not. The caſe ſtanding thus, let the Reader judge who are more like the Phariſees, <hi>that rejected the counſel of God againſt themſelves, in not being baptized of John,</hi> whether ſuch as would practice according to their Judgement, or ſuch as oppoſe and hinder them from ſo doing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Neglect is not ſo great for thirty years, as is Objected: for, in the former years of theſe Plantations, till the Church-ſeed were grown up to Marry, and have Children, there was not ſuch need of practice according to the fifth Propoſition (which is now moſt ſtumbled at;) beſides, ſome Churches have been in that practice for divers years.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is <hi>no falling from our former practice,</hi> as is Objected, our Principles are the ſame; this is onely a progreſs in practiſing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording thereunto, as the encreaſe of the Churches doth require. It is the way of Chriſt in the Goſpel, to ſet up the practice of his Inſtitutions as the neceſſities of the people call for them, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.36, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with 10.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Acts</hi> 6.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When Circumciſion, by reaſon of the travels in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, was omitted forty years, and the Feaſt of Tabernacles from the dayes of <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the dayes of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> was neglected ſo many hundreds of years, we do not reade of ſo deep a charge laid upon the Elders and People by any of the Prophets of God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, We are charged with <q>
                     <hi>A greater ſin to be trembled at,</hi> viz. <hi>That we admitted all ſorts that were perſonally in Covenant to the Lords Supper, which now we deny to many, except after Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they make it manifeſt, that they are able to examine themſelves, and diſcern the Lords Body: If this be regular, then the other is irregular,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:191784:7"/>and brought guiltineſs to many of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and was eating and drinking judgement to our ſelves.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is a very heavy Imputation laid upon ſo many Elders and Churches, and without any colour of Reaſon: For, what mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is it whether Elders and Churches be ſatisfied of the fitneſs of their Members for the Lords Supper, before their admittance into the Church, by the Elders examination of them; or at their admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by their publick Profeſſions (which is known to be our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant care and practice) or afterward? but becauſe we do it not after Covenanting in perſons received in adult age, as well as in perſons received in infancy, that therefore we are ſo deeply guilty; this is a groſs and irregular Charge. Some have objected againſt our admiſſions, as over-ſtrict; but who hath charged us with ſuch <hi>a ſin to be trembled at</hi> in ſuch a manner, as <hi>to bring guiltineſs upon many of the Body and Blood of Chriſt?</hi> And it is ſtrange to ſee ſuch as make ſo loud a Profeſſion of <hi>ſtedfaſtneſs in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel,</hi> to lay ſo great a Scandal of <hi>a ſin to be trembled at,</hi> upon ſo many Elders, before conviction thereof, and their impenitency therein, and that in the face of <hi>Old England</hi> and <hi>New,</hi> ſo contrary to the principal and expreſs Rules of Goſpel-order, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18 15, 16. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, In the Anſwer to the ſecond Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>That by Publiſhing this Treatiſe they ſhall diſturb the peace,</hi> &amp;c.</q> The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor pleading poſſeſſion of another manner of diſpenſing the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and that <hi>bought at a great rate, The loſs of Native Land, Fathers Houſes,</hi> &amp;c. he ſaith, <q>
                     <hi>That the diſturbers of the peace, the troublers of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>are thoſe that would rob them of their poſſeſſion, or queſtion their right, especially having enjoyed them ſo long before this pleaded-for Converſion of</hi> New England.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. But did we indeed come to <hi>New England</hi> to put our Poſterity under the wings of Gods gracious Covenant and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and then to deny them and their ſeed the Benefits thereof? to leave them at a looſe end without the Diſcipline of Chriſt, the Means to prevent ſin, or to reduce them to Repentance unto life? Certainly, the Profeſſion of very many gracious and ſerious hearts, and their hopes for their Children, was farre otherwiſe. Yea, of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191784:7"/>theſe that now Diſſent amongſt us, ſome I know, and many more I may ſuppoſe left <hi>Old England</hi> for the good of their ſeed in this reſpect.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Are not our Children in poſſeſſion of the Houſe, Members of the Church, by the confeſſion of the Diſſenters? The Synod pleadeth onely <hi>that they may enjoy the Priviledges of the Houſe;</hi> it is the Diſſenters therefore <hi>that would rob them of their poſſeſſion, and diſturb the peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Synod (as appeareth in their Preface) doth leave them to their liberty to practiſe according to their Judgement: If they will not own, or Baptize ſuch as in the fifth Propoſition are deſcribed; if they will have their Children accounted <hi>Self-murtherers, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covenanted of God, if the Lord have not wrought Faith and Repentance viſibly in them when they come to adult age,</hi> there is none that offereth to diſturb their poſſeſſion in theſe things. And why then ſhould they diſturb and oppoſe the Right and Poſſeſſion of ſo many others who aſſert the Rights of the Church-ſeed, which are in Covenant with God in poſſeſſion of the Houſe, whoſe <hi>advantage</hi> (the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith) <hi>and profit is much every way?</hi> Rom. 3.1, 2.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, In Anſwer to the third Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>That they are Innovators;</hi> and <hi>that the moſt learned M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>niſters were of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods minde.</hi>
                  </q> This Author of the Preface granting this to be true of <hi>Some,</hi> (which is a <hi>large Some,</hi> as is manifeſt in the Preface to the Synod) he muſt needs caſt a double Aſperſion upon the Elders, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>
                     <hi>That as many of them are ſo large in Judgement, as to ſoulder with Pariſh Churches.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> If this be meant in reſpect of Communion with Orthodox Pariſh Churches, we are no larger then our Diſſenting Brethren, who concur with us in the ſeventh Propoſition about the firſt Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which ſpeaks to this caſe. But if it be meant of <hi>inlarging the Church to the Bounds of a Pariſh,</hi> it is a meer Slander: I do not believe that he can prove that any two Elders of theſe Churches have ſo declared their Judgement; much leſs ſo many as are of the Synods minde. It lieth upon the Author to make good this charge, or to recant his raſhneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:191784:8"/> 2. He affirmeth, <q>
                     <hi>That the general Judgement of the learned El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and their Practice, was as the Diſſenters plead; but now divers of thoſe Elders do retreat and recant.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To prove this, he alledgeth two Paſſages out of <hi>An Anſwer to Thirty two Queſtions,</hi> Printed 1639. But thoſe Paſſages are too weak to bear up this Aſſertion; yea, do evidence the quite contrary.</p>
               <p>The firſt is taken out of <hi>Page</hi> 22. of the ſaid Book; the ſum whereof is this, <q>
                     <hi>That ſuch whoſe Parents are not Believers and ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fied, are not foederally holy; Foederal Holineſs or Sanctity being limited to the next Parents,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. This Paſſage doth not agree with the Diſſenters; for it doth appear, that the Author doth account Foederal Holineſs to be Sanctity: and therefore the next parents being in Covenant with God, and ſo continuing, they are Eccleſiaſtically holy, ſanctified, and viſible Believers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do not the ſame Elders in this Synod deliver the very ſame Doctrine, in the <hi>ſecond Propoſition,</hi> and <hi>fifth particular,</hi> viz. <hi>It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to the Memberſhip of Children, that the next Parents, one or both, be in Covenant?</hi> Citing the ſame Text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. And where then is the leaſt ſhew of Recanting?</p>
               <p>The ſecond Proof is <hi>Page</hi> 23. of the ſaid Book, where it is ſaid, that <q>
                     <hi>We believe that all Members of Churches ought to be Saints, and faithful in Chriſt Jeſus, none excepted,</hi> Epheſ. 1.1. 1 Cor. 1.2. Phil. 1.1:</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. This paſſage ſpeaketh of Members to be admitted in adult age, and therefore might be as well alledged to prove a conſent with the Anabaptiſts, as with the Diſſenters; which was farre from the meaning of that Author. Beſides, though they ought to be ſo, yet that denieth not, but being regularly admitted, they are ſtill Members of the Church, till they be regularly caſt out, though they do not approve themſelves to be ſuch.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do not thoſe Elders profeſs the ſame Doctrine in the Synod, <hi>Propoſ.</hi> 2. viz <hi>Members of the viſible Church, according to Scripture, are Confederate viſible Believers?</hi> alledging the ſame Texts, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where then is this Recantation?</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The Author of this Preface excuſing <hi>the Paucity of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191784:8"/>Diſſenters, in compariſon of the many able, learned, and godly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Miniſters that conſented;</hi> He objecteth three things againſt the Synod conſenting.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>
                     <hi>That divers of the Elders having Preached and Practiſed that Doctrine of late years, were pre-engaged: and it is ſtrange that after Vows they ſhould be called to enquire.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Were not <hi>Paul, Barnabas,</hi> and others, as much engaged in the Doctrine of that Synod <hi>Acts</hi> 15? and did they come <hi>after V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ws to enquire?</hi> 2. Were not the Diſſenters as much pre-engaged in their Opinion? why then did they come <hi>after Vows to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is Objected, <q>
                     <hi>That divers Meſſengers being no Logicians to anſwer Syllogiſms, and diſcern Ambiguities, were over-born by the many Oppoſers.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is incongruous and too high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to make the Body of the Synod the <hi>Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſers,</hi> which more fitly agree to th few Diſſenters. 2. Though divers were not ſuch Logicians, yet Charity might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the choyce Members of our Churches to be able to judge of Arguments drawn from the Scriptures; and ſo farre conſciencious, as that diſcerning the Voice of Chriſt, they would not be born down with number of Oppoſers. To ſay nothing of the Logick of the Diſſenters, that might be as little as the others.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is Objected, <q>
                     <hi>That the corruption of man moſt inclineth to walk in the broadeſt way, though the ſtraiter way be never ſo clear; especially when perſons eminent in Place, Power, Learning and Piety, are ſo linked together?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Be it ſo, that there is ſuch a corruption in man: yet when ſuch perſons (as the Synod are confeſſed to be) agree in one, and that in ſo Solemn an Ordinance of God, where Chriſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed his Preſence; <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y, that hopeth all things,</hi> might well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Grace would prevail above ſuch a Corruption. 2 If our Brother be not aware of it, I can aſſure him that there is alſo a Corruption in man, and in good men too, under the not on of <hi>Strictneſs and Zeal,</hi> to ſwerve as much to the other Extreme: As when the Diſciples would have <hi>kept little children from Chriſt,</hi> Mark 10.13, 14. When out of zeal againſt the <hi>Tares,</hi> men would hazard
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191784:9"/>to <hi>plack up the Wheat alſo,</hi> Matth. 13.28, 29. So when we are <hi>apt to judge others, whom God hath received,</hi> Rom. 14.3. which I wiſh our Brother ſeriouſly to conſider. The way of the Anabaptiſts is a <hi>ſtraiter way,</hi> yet I ſuppoſe this Brother doth not judge it <hi>his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> to chuſe a way ſomewhat larger. So is the way of the <hi>Seekers</hi> and others, who think their ſtraiter wayes as clear as our Brother thinketh of his.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, In <hi>Page</hi> 5. this Brother anſwering another Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <q>
                     <hi>That this Diſcourſe may ſeem needleſs, ſeeing all other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Churches agree with them, that they know of;</hi>
                  </q> alledging the <hi>Savoy Meeting,</hi> Chap. 29. Of Baptiſm 4. <q>
                     <hi>Yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>there needs abundant confirmation: for no doubt this temptation will ſpread further, when more then the third part of the Stars of Heaven here are ſwept down, as is Propheſied</hi> Rev. 12. &amp;c. <hi>Furthermore,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>let the world know, That the Lord hath ſtill a few Names in</hi> New England <hi>who hold faſt his Name, and are ſtedfaſt in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel, and deteſt the Abominations of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. This Author glorieth much in the <hi>Conſent of other Churches.</hi> We ſee here his ground, which I ſhall examine. The Poſition of that Meeting of the Churches, is this: <hi>Not onely thoſe that do actually profeſs Faith in, and Obedience unto Chriſt; but alſo the Infants of one or both believing Parents, are to be Baptized, and thoſe onely.</hi> We can well conſent with this Doctrine, without any prejudice to the Doctrine of the Synod: For we profeſs and prove in the Synod, That the children of the Church being in Covenant with God, owned by him as holy, as his People, his Children, and manifeſting their continuance in the Covenant, according to the fifth Propoſition, theſe are viſible Believers in Eccleſiaſtical ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in Scripture account, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. with 7.14. And I cannot believe but that Reverend and Learned Aſſembly would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Regular Church-members to be viſible Believers:</hi> And it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that theſe are Regular Church-members in their judgement, by their <hi>Second Poſition, Concerning the Church,</hi> Chap. 26. where they ſay, <hi>All ſuch as profeſs the Faith of the Goſpel, and Obedience to God by Chriſt according to it, not deſtroying their Profeſſion by Errours
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191784:9"/>everting the Foundation, or unholineſs of Converſation, are Members of the viſible Church.</hi> Now it cannot be denied that the perſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the fifth Propoſition of the Synod are ſuch, for <hi>they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs their Aſſent to the Doctrine of Faith, and ſubjection to the Rules and Diſcipline of Chriſt; they give up themſelves to God, own the Covenant, do not deſtroy their Profeſſion by Errours, nor unholineſs of life; holding the Doctrine of Faith, and not being ſcandalous in life.</hi> So that for ought that appears, that Aſſembly agreeth rather with the Synod, then with the Diſſenters.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that our Brother maketh ſuch a diſtinction between <hi>the third part of the Stars of</hi> New-England <hi>ſwept down,</hi> and <hi>A few Names in</hi> New-England <hi>that hold faſt the Name of God, and are ſtedfaſt in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel:</hi> How well this Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reeth with the Rules of Charity, Humility and Modeſty, I ſhall leave to the judgement of others.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I muſt enquire into the Truth and Grounds of ſo deep a Charge, laid upon more then <hi>the third part of the Stars,</hi> the Lights ſet up in the Churches of <hi>New-England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it the preſent Doctrine of this Synod, inlarging the Subject of Baptiſm beyond the Opinion of the Diſſenters, that is <hi>their fall from Heaven?</hi> And the more ſtrict Opinion of our Brethren, the Character of thoſe <hi>few Names remaining that hold faſt the Faith and Order of the Gospel?</hi> as indeed it ſeemeth to be ſo. For, 1. This is the occaſion taken up to make this Compariſon. And 2. Thoſe other Imputations, of <hi>Forſaking former P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>actices, Recanting of Elders, New Converſion of</hi> New-England, in reference to this Doctrine, ſeem to intimate as much. 3. And that Expreſſion of <hi>a few Names holding faſt the Faith and Order of the Goſpel,</hi> doth plainly intimate, that not only <hi>more then a third part of the Stars,</hi> but alſo the generality of <hi>New England</hi> are greatly departed from <hi>the Faith and Order of the Gospel,</hi> and that, at the preſent, in the judgement of this Author: which is ſo high a ſtrain, that I am loth to ſay what might be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of it.</p>
               <p>Now if this be our <hi>Fall from Heaven,</hi> it is our comfort that we are not yet faln ſo farre as many bright Stars of the firſt Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that have ſhined gloriouſly in the Churches; ſuch as <hi>Calvin,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191784:10"/>Cartwright, Perkins, Ames,</hi> and hundreds more, whoſe judgement is well known to be larger in this Point then the Synod doth hold forth. And we are faln no further then bleſſed <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ton, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lip, Shepard, Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers,</hi> and others of the Bay Churches: Famous <hi>Hooker</hi> and <hi>Stone</hi> of <hi>Connectico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Prudden</hi> of <hi>New-Haven, Partridge</hi> and <hi>Newman</hi> of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> with divers other Lights in <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w-England,</hi> of whom I am perſwaded that they are gotten to Heaven in that Opinion, whereby we are ſuppoſed to be <hi>ſwept down from Heaven.</hi> But let this Brother beware, leſt himſelf and his <hi>few Names</hi> be not judged by ſome to be <hi>ſwept down from Heaven</hi> alſo, who hold an Opinion, <hi>That Infants of the Church are to be Baptized,</hi> which is not ſo ſtrict a Tenent as they would have.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But if this ſo great a Charge be laid upon <hi>more then the third part of the Stars</hi> upon any other ground, let it be conſidered whether the <hi>Rules of Charity and Gospel-Order</hi> would not require, that he ſhould firſt have Convinced his Brethren of their <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> (yea, indeed of their ſuppoſed Errour about <hi>the Subject of Baptiſm</hi>) before he ſhould caſt ſo great a Scandal upon them before the face of the world; even <hi>an Heretick</hi> may have <hi>two Admonitions before rejection.</hi> However, whether it be this or that ground, ſurely this courſe doth not a little darken that loud Profeſſion of our Brother's <hi>holding faſt to the Order of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath been our portion all along, to go <hi>through evil Reports</hi> from the mouthes of many diſcontented perſons, and corrupt <hi>Opinioniſts, Familiſts, Anabaptiſts, Quakers,</hi> and the like; but I little expected ſuch things as theſe from ſo near a Friend and Brother. I will not deny or excuſe the Declining of many Profeſſors to corrupt Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to the World, Looſe Wayes, and the like: Neither will I juſtifie all things in all the Elders of <hi>New-England;</hi> failings may be found in Judgement and Practice, and perhaps ſome may be larger in their Judgement concerning <hi>The Subject of Baptiſm,</hi> then the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod doth hold forth: But God forbid we ſhould judge them to be <hi>ſwept down from Heaven,</hi> that differ from us in greater matters then theſe, or for ſuch Blemiſhes as are incident to good men. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the generality of the Stars in <hi>New-England</hi> Churches be not yet in the right hand of Chriſt, ſhining in their Orbs with the light
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:191784:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Heavenly Doctrine, and Chriſtian Converſation, I appeal to the Conſciences of all the ſober-minded People of God in the Country; yea, and alſo to the Conſcience of the Author of this Preface him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who gives this Teſtimony of the Elders in the Synod, being more then half the Elders of all the Churches of <hi>New-England,</hi> pag. 5. <hi>viz. That they were able, learned and godly;</hi> and again, <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in Learning and Piety.</hi> However it be, it is a very <hi>little thing to be judged of men,</hi> whether approved or condemned.</p>
               <p>Concerning that which is ſaid of Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> by name, for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing a Book in favour of Epiſcopacy; our Brother doth or might know, that the Book is diſtaſtful alſo to his Brethren, as well as to himſelf: yet the approved Learning and Piety of the perſon might have called for better language.</p>
               <p>As for that Imputation, <q>
                     <hi>That the Common-Prayer-Book findeth ſome Advocates in</hi> New-England, <hi>who can finde Stakes and Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials to edifie Gods People in a Congregational Church (as is ſaid.)</hi>
                  </q> I wonder that a man of Piety and Gravity ſhould venture to publiſh ſuch things to the world upon <hi>(As is ſaid;)</hi> and to what end is it, except to caſt dirt upon his Brethren? Much more then is true, is ſaid of that and other things. The Lord help ſuch as profeſs ſuch <hi>ſtedfaſtneſs in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel,</hi> to walk up to the Rules of Goſpel-Order and Charity, more then this Brother hath done.</p>
               <p>Thus much to the firſt Preface. Concerning the ſecond, <hi>To the General Court,</hi> I ſhall Animadvert onely upon two or three Paſſages of it. And</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whereas <hi>pag.</hi> 8. they tell the Honoured Court, <q>
                     <hi>That they have yielded and voted with the reſt ſo farre, that rightly conſidered and practiſed, it would ſilence all ſad Complaints againſt the many great and prevailing corruptions of Youth amongst us.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is true, that one of the chief of our Diſſenting Brethren did propound, and earneſtly promote the third Propoſition; <hi>viz. That the Infant-ſeed of the Church are Members of the ſame Church with their Parents, and when they are grown up, are perſonally under the Watch and Government of the Church:</hi> and this rightly practiſed, would indeed tend much to the end aforeſaid; for ſo the Church, by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:191784:11"/>an Ordinance of Chriſt that hath his Promiſe annexed, ſhould either bring ſuch Youth to Repentance, or purge the Church of them. But it is as true, that this Treatiſe putteth ſuch a ſenſe and meaning upon that Propoſition, as renders it uſeleſs and vain to the ends afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. For, if they be not actual, perſonal, nor <hi>immediate Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> whereby acts of Church-government ſhould be put forth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately upon their perſons, but onely reach them at the ſecond hand, <hi>viz</hi> by their Parents, as was ſaid by ſome in the Meeting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, to which they referre, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. And if Excommunication, that healing Medicine of Chriſt <hi>for the deſtruction of the fleſh, and ſaving of the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l,</hi> may not touch them, as is in the ſame <hi>Page</hi> 23. Yea, if the Foederal Holineſs of their perſons, and ſo their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-intereſt, continue no longer then their minority, (wherein indeed they are ſcarce capable of any Church diſcipline) as is affirmed <hi>Page</hi> 37.) Theſe things being ſo, let any man judge how it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for Church-government to reform ſuch <hi>great, many, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing corruptions of Youth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Page</hi> 10. our Brethren ſay, <q>
                     <hi>It is apparent to all, what a corrupt maſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers ſhall by this change throng into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of Gods People, and the children of ſtrangers, uncircumciſed in heart, ſhall be brought into Gods Sanctuary to pollute it, contrary to</hi> Ezek 44.7, 9.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Whether theſe Parents in queſtion be to be counted <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> or not, will appear after. But if the Charity of our Brethren will allow them no other term, I pray, Who let them <hi>into the fellowſhip of Gods People?</hi> Do not our Brethren with us affirm, That the Covenant of <hi>Abraham</hi> belongs unto them, and therefore they are to partake of Baptiſm the Seal of it? <hi>And</hi> (ſay they) <hi>there is the whole Churches Communion in Baptiſm, as well as in the Lords Supper,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. If then they would keep them out of <hi>the fellowſhip of Gods People,</hi> they muſt joyn with thoſe that ſhut that door againſt all Infants by which they entred; for if they be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers</hi> that are ſo qualified as in Propoſition the fifth, then ſurely they were ſo when they were Baptized. By this, with many other Paſſages, our Brethren may ſee whither their Principles do carry them. So that the difference between the Synod and our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:191784:11"/>Brethren, is not about their <hi>Admiſſion into the fellowſhip of Gods People,</hi> but about <hi>The Improvement of the Ordinances of Chriſt for their good, while they continue in that fellowſhip;</hi> wherein the Synods Doctrine admits them not to acts of Communion with the reſt of Gods People, but as they are regularly fit; neither do the Synod continue them in that fellowſhip, any longer then they walk orderly, without deſerving the Cenſures of the Church. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. ſpeaks of <hi>ſtrangers amongst the children of Iſrael,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Tobiah, Neh</hi> 13.4 &amp;c. not of any Iſraelite, <hi>ver.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our Brethren in their ſixth Conſideration, acknowledging <q>
                     <hi>The great Deliverances and Wonders that the Lord hath wrought in former times for</hi> New England; they adde, <hi>But ſince the motion of this Change, what the Lords dealing hath been and ſtill is, we leave to the prudent to judge: We may glory in this New Light, but we fear it will prove but glorying in our ſhame.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I had thought that Gods gracious anſwer to the Prayers of the Synod 1662. in ſending Rain ſo ſpeedily and ſweetly, might not onely have taken off that Imputation of the Drought unto the Synod, as if it was for their ſakes; but alſo it might have ſtayed our Brethren from ſuch Applications of the Providences of God to their own ends. I remember that when the <hi>Popiſh Cantons</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted the death of <hi>Zuinglius</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecolampadius</hi> to the juſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God upon them for cauſing their Troubles, the Hiſtorian hath this Obſervation upon it: <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a pious thought to attribute the diſpoſition of every Event to the Providence of God; but to determine to what ends thoſe Events are directed by his high Wiſdome, is not farre from Preſumption. Men are ſo ſtraightly and religiouſly wedded to their own Opinions, that they are perſwaded God loveth and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth them as much as themſelves.</hi> Hiſt. of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> p. 60. But if we muſt needs take notice of the dealing, of God with <hi>Non-England,</hi> in reference to this caſe; Can any prudent man ſay, that the Deliverances of <hi>New-England</hi> are not as g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful in theſe laſt years, and at this day, as in former years? And as for thoſe afflicting Providences that have lately b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>faln us, have we not had as heavy Strokes many wayes formerly? And have we not Sins enough that are evident, to humble us under the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:191784:12"/>Lords hand, as deſerving theſe and greater evils, but we muſt needs apply them as Judgements of God to this (falſly ſo called) Change, and brand the conſtant Doctrine of Gods eminent Meſſengers amongſt us, as a <hi>New Light that will turn to our ſhame?</hi> The Lord forgive theſe many harſh Cenſures of the Brethren.</p>
               <p>Thus have I paſſed through this unpleaſing part of my Work: wherein, if by clearing the innocent, any thing doth reflect upon the Accuſers, I hope the equal-minded Reader will excuſe me; conſidering, that the Name of God is named upon the Elders and Churches of <hi>New-England,</hi> and would have ſuffered in them, ſhould not ſuch unjuſt Aſperſions be wiped off them by a juſt Apologie. Had our Brethren followed the Example of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, with like Love, Tenderneſs and Moderation as is expreſſed towards them in their Preface, the world had not been ſo Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized as I fear it is, by theſe Conteſts, and I had ſpared much of this labour. Oh! when ſhall we ſee Brethren manage ſuch Diſputes with that Brotherly Love, Ingenuity, and Endeavours to finde out the Truth, as becometh the Cauſe of CHRIST, and without ſuch harſh Reflections upon mens perſons! The want of this <hi>is a Lamentation, and ſhall be for a Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:191784:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Concerning our Brethrens Anſwer to the main Queſtion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COncerning <hi>The Order of this Treatiſe,</hi> I need not trouble the Reader; nor concerning their two Propoſitions premiſed. Who doubteth that <hi>Baptiſm is a Seal of the Gospel, and to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred according to Goſpel-Rules?</hi> Or, <hi>that the ſureſt way to end Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, is to finde out how it was in the beginning?</hi> Onely theſe Rules are too general, and have a like influence into all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies about Goſpel-Ordinances.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore endeavour to clear up from Scripture two or three Propoſitions, that have a more near and immediate reſpect to the Queſtion now in debate. It is no queſtion between us, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adult perſons to be joyned to the Church, and to be Baptized, ſhould hold forth Faith and Repentance to the judgement of Charity, and that in ſome particular viſible Church?</hi> nor, <hi>Whether the Infant-ſeed of ſuch are to be Baptized?</hi> But, the very Hinge whereupon our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate turneth, lieth in theſe two things:
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Whether the Infant-ſeed of all Church-members ought to be Baptized?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>What it is that Cuts off any from his Memberſhip in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church?</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Clear up theſe two from the Word of God; and the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie is iſſued. To this end I ſhall premiſe three things, which being proved by the Word of God, will make my way plain and eaſie through all theſe <hi>Antiſynodalia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Propoſ. </seg>1</label> That however the Memberſhip of the ſeed of the Faithful be conveyed to them by their Parents inſtrumentally, yet it flows from, and is grounded upon Gods Inſtitution, as the principal Efficient
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:191784:13"/>cauſe thereof, who is pleaſed to extend the Grace of his Covenant not only to the Parents, but alſo to their ſeed. God enters into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with them, <hi>He is their God, They are his People.</hi> This is evident <hi>Gen.</hi> 17 7. <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between Me and Thee, and thy ſeed after thee, to be a God to thee, and to thy ſeed after thee:</hi> At eight dayes old they were to be Circumciſed, as a Token of the Covenant between God and them, <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29 11, 12. <hi>Their little ones ſtood before the Lord their God, to enter into Covenant with the Lord their God, to be eſtabliſhed a people to himſelf.</hi> What can be ſpoken more plainly and fully to this purpoſe? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>The Promiſe is to your Children.</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. <hi>Your Children are holy.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, what can be ſuppoſed in the Parents Faith, Profeſſion, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting to bring in their ſeed, but it dependeth wholly upon Gods Free-grace, ordaining his Covenant ſo to be diſpenſed? And hence it followeth, That the Infant-ſeed are in their own perſons actually Members of the Church, being actually in this Covenant with God as <hi>His People,</hi> and he <hi>Their God,</hi> and having the Covenant in their fleſh, the Seal of it applied to their perſons. And hence they cannot be cut off from their intereſt in God, and his Covenant-Priviledges, but in ſuch a way as he hath ordained, which in Goſpel-times is by Church-cenſures. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Propoſ. </seg>2</label> There is a twofold Diſpenſation of the Covenant of God in his viſible Church: 1. Outward and viſible, by which the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows upon his Church, and all the Members thereof, the outward Priviledges of the Covenant, his Ordinances, and Means of Grace, as they become capable thereof, and wherein he tenders unto them the Saving Benefits thereof, with many Means to bring up their hearts to the embracing thereof. This is evident, they have all the Name and Title of <hi>Gods People, His Children, A Royal Prieſthood, Holy Nation, Saints,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5, 6. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.1, 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.26. And the Ordinances and Means of Grace are theirs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.4. So in the New-Teſtament, the whole Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> are called <hi>Saints, and faithful in Chriſt.</hi> The Seven Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. are called <hi>Golden Candleſticks,</hi> though there were corrupt Members in them. And the Miniſtry of the Word, and other Ordinances, belong to the viſible
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:191784:13"/>Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Whence it is evident, That Officers are ſet in the Church <hi>for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt,</hi> and for the healing and ſaving the Members of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a more Inward, Spiritual, and Saving Diſpenſation of the Covenant to ſuch as truly Believe, and perform the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Covenant, whoſe hearts God hath circumciſed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Promiſes of the Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. From this different Diſpenſation it is, that the Lord, though he requires of all to <hi>Fear the Lord their God,</hi> to <hi>Walk in his wayes,</hi> to <hi>Love him with all their hearts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12, 13. and <hi>keepeth Covenant and Mercy with them that love God, and walk with God in faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;</hi> but reproveth the wicked <hi>for taking his Covenant into their mouthes,</hi> Pſal. 50. rejects their Sacrifices, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 58. calleth them <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed, Ethiopians,</hi> &amp;c. in reſpect of any inward and ſaving Benefits of the Covenant: yet ſtill he owneth them as <hi>His People, Saints in Covenant with him,</hi> Pſal. 50.1. and followeth them with the Means of Grace till there be no remedy, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. This is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in all the ſtory of the Church in the Old and New-Teſtament, as will appear more afterward.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Propoſ. </seg>3</label> There is a different Rule and Reaſon of admitting Members into the viſible Church, and the continuation of them in it, being regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly admitted. In <hi>Admitting Members into the Church,</hi> we juſtly look for ſuch poſitive Qualifications as the Word of God requireth, viz. <hi>A viſible Profeſſion of Faith and Repentance in adult perſons, and Foederal Holineſs in Infants.</hi> We well approve that Saying of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mier,</hi> quoted by our Brethren, <q>
                     <hi>No man can diſallow ſuch diligence, to prevent the profaning of holy things, and leſt ſuch as</hi> Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus <hi>ſhould lie hid.</hi>
                  </q> But to caſt out ſuch as are <hi>Regularly admitted,</hi> we muſt have poſitive Impenitency in ſin, as a ground to <hi>count them as Heathens and Publicans, Mat.</hi> 18. and that after due patience towards them; for, even <hi>an Heretick may have two Admonitions before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> Tit. 3.10. or at leaſt ſome notorious ſcandalous ſin, as ſome conceive from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Theſe things premiſed, I ſhall proceed to conſider the next
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:191784:14"/>thing in order, which is our Brethrens <hi>Anſwer to the main Queſtion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> viz. <hi>Who are the Subjects of Baptiſm?</hi> To which their Anſwer i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>That viſible Believers and Converts in full Communion with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Church, (being unbaptized) together with their next ſeed in minority, are the proper and immediate Subjects of Baptiſm, as to the receiving of it.</hi>
                  </q> For the proof of this, they referre to the places before alledged, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. Their large Diſcourſe I paſs by, though ſome things might be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Diſpute: but I would decline all impertinencies, and come to their Reaſon gathered out of thoſe Scriptures; which is this:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Thoſe are proper and immediate Subjects of Baptiſm, to whom Chriſt, in the Goſpel-inſtitution, hath appointed it. But viſible Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers and Converts in full Communion with an inſtituted Church, are the perſons (being unbaptized) to whom Chriſt, in the Goſpel-inſtitution of Baptiſm, hath appointed it.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Therefore viſible Believers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The greateſt weight or ſtreſs of this Argument, lieth upon that place <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. and I ſee our Brethren put much confidence in it, affirming, <q>
                     <hi>That the</hi> minor <hi>is expreſs Scripture, and therefore though many are unwilling it ſhould be true, and will cavill againſt it, it will be found true at the Day of Judgement,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> God forbid, that in ſearching after the Truth we ſhould <hi>Cavill</hi> at the Word of God; but let us take heed of <hi>Adding to it,</hi> or <hi>Taking from it:</hi> But whether the <hi>Minor</hi> will prove true, or not, we need not ſtay till the <hi>Day of Judgement;</hi> for, the holy Scriptures, the Judge of all Controverſies, will eaſily decide it; and I will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly deny the <hi>Minor:</hi> for none of thoſe Scriptures, or any other that I know of, will prove, <hi>That full communion with an inſtituted Church is requiſite to the Subject of Baptiſm,</hi> much leſs <hi>that ſuch are the proper Subjects thereof;</hi> as if ſuch, and onely ſuch, were to be Baptized. This of <hi>Full Communion</hi> our Brethren thought would advantage their Cauſe, and ſo have put it in: but it is a meer Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to the Word of God, which wholly fails them of any proof, yea makes evidently againſt them. In that principal place, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. it is evident, that they were Baptized before their <hi>Full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion:</hi> For, 1. <hi>Peter</hi> called them to be Baptized upon the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:191784:14"/>ground of the Promiſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 38. 2. They were <hi>Baptized, and added to the Church,</hi> before full Communion, <hi>ver.</hi> 41, 42. 3. It had been very prepoſterous to put them into full Communion, before <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with the Church ſealed by Baptiſm;</hi> for <hi>Baptiſm is a Seal of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with the Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. which muſt go before Communion. But they ſeem to ſuppoſe, at leaſt, that ſome in full Communion may be unbaptized, by that word <hi>(being unbaptized:)</hi> but the truth is, that our Brethrens confidence in this Argument will be found ſo greatly to fail them, that whil'ſt by it they ſeek to ſtraiten <hi>The Subject of Baptiſm,</hi> beyond the Doctrine of the Synod, they deſtroy and take away the <hi>whole Subject it ſelf of Baptiſm,</hi> becauſe there will never be found any ſuch perſons, according to <hi>Gospel-Rule,</hi> (which they call ſo much for, and appeal unto) that are in <hi>full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with an inſtituted Church, being unbaptized.</hi> I will be a little bold with our Brethren in this caſe, to challenge them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any Rule or Example in the Goſpel, of any perſon that either was, or by Rule might be in <hi>full Communion with an inſtituted Church, being unbaptized.</hi> I hope this Anſwer is plain, and no <hi>Cavill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet for the further clearing up of this Anſwer, I ſhall remove what may be further ſaid by our Brethren.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Though thoſe in</hi> Acts 2. <hi>were not in full Communion actually before Baptiſm, yet they were admitted to a ſtate and right to full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion by their Baptiſm, which theſe Children in queſtion are not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The Queſtion is not, <hi>What ſtate or right the Baptized are partakers of, as a conſequent fruit of Baptiſm received?</hi> but, <hi>What it is that conſtitutes a perſon to be a fit Subject to be Baptized?</hi> To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the proper <hi>Subject of Baptiſm,</hi> by the conſequent fruits of it, and not by the precedent cauſes that gives right to Baptiſm, is very improper and prepoſterous. If the Queſtion were, <hi>Who are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Subjects of Church-memberſhip?</hi> we ſay, <hi>Confederating viſible Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and their ſeed;</hi> for this makes them fit for, and brings them into ſuch a relation. But ſhould any anſwer, <hi>That the proper Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Church-memberſhip, is a perſon in full communion with an inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Church;</hi> or, <hi>One that is under the Teaching and Rule of Church-Officers, which are the fruits of Church-memberſhip received:</hi> Who
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:191784:15"/>does not ſee the weakneſs of ſuch an Anſwer? and the like is this caſe, Baptiſm being the Seal of Gods Covenant with his Church, whereby <hi>we are Baptized into one Body.</hi> 2. Although the Infant-ſeed of the Church cannot actually enjoy full Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in all Ordinances, as their Parents do; yet the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God ſealed to them in Baptiſm, ſets them in <hi>a ſtate and right</hi> to all the Benefits of the Covenant, to be enjoyed by them as they become fit for them, as well as their Parents: for, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God with Parents and ſeed, is one and the ſame. All that are in the ſame Covenant, are bound to the ſame Duties of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and have the ſame right to all the Benefits of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as they come up to perform the Conditions, and are fit for the enjoyment of the Bleſſings. In adult Members it is ſo, who being under Admonition for Scandal, or in a Frenzy, or the like caſe, though they partake not of all the good of the Covenant, yet their right remains: So here, when the ſeed grow up to perform the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Covenant, they alſo partake of the Benefits, not by any new Covenant, or Memberſhip, but by the right of that Covenant God made with them, and ſealed to them in Baptiſm, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more fully afterward.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I ſhall adde further, It is true, that to admit adult perſons into the Church, and to Baptiſm, viſible Faith is required; and ſo much the Texts alledged prove: but this is not the caſe in Diſpute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, but <hi>About perſons already in the Church, and Baptized, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſuch, the ground of Baptizing their ſeed, be Faith and Grace made viſible in the ſame manner,</hi> or <hi>their Intereſt in the Covenant?</hi> and therefore the Argument doth not conclude the Queſtion. Put caſe any of thoſe <hi>viſible Believers and converts,</hi> Acts 2. ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſcover by their Worldlineſs, Looſeneſs, or other wayes, that there is in them no ſap or ſavour of Faith and Grace, even to the charitable judgement of moſt in the Church; my Queſtion is, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet (ſo long as they continue in the Church) their Infant-ſeed ſhall not be Baptized?</hi> If it be granted, then it is not ſuch viſible Faith and Grace, but the Intereſt in the Church and Covenant that gives <hi>Right to Baptiſm,</hi> and ſo to theſe Church-members in queſtion. If this be denied, let there be one Tittle of Scripture-Rule or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191784:15"/>produced to the contrary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Having anſwered their Reaſon, I ſhall preſent an Argument from the ſame Text, to confirm the Doctrine of the Synod. It is to be noted, That the Promiſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. is <hi>That Covenant-Promiſe which God made with</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, as appeareth by that parallel place, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. where <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts to Repentance, as in <hi>chap.</hi> 2.38. and <hi>chap.</hi> 3.25. he uſeth the ſame Reaſon in other words, <hi>You are the children of the Covenant which God made with our fathers;</hi> the ſubſtance whereof all grant to be this, <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed in their generations</hi> (although the Apoſtle there makes uſe of another branch of the Covenant concerning Chriſt, that feed in whom <hi>God is the God of his People.</hi>) Now the Reaſon ſtands thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the Covenant-promiſe to</hi> Abraham <hi>and his ſeed, be a ground to Repent and be Baptizſed in the Goſpel-diſpenſation, then it is the Covenant of God with his viſible Church that gives right to Baptiſm. But the Covenant-promiſe was a ground to Repent and be Baptized, in Gospel-diſpenſation,</hi> Acts 2.38, 39. with <hi>chap.</hi> 3.19, 25. <hi>Therefore it is the Covenant of God with his viſible Church, that gives right to Baptiſm:</hi> which is the Doctrine of the Synod.</p>
               <p>Thus much to their Scripture-Argument. To which our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren adde the Teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Richard Mather:</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Well agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with this</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is the Anſwer of Reverend Mr.</hi> Mather <hi>in his Catechiſm.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But, by their leave, it differeth from their Anſwer in the main thing that toucheth the cauſe in hand; for, there is nothing of <hi>full communion</hi> in his, which they put into theirs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Reverend and Learned Author ſpeaketh onely what adult perſons ſhould be, in joyning to the Church, and the ſeed of ſuch ſo converted and joyned, which hath reference to their firſt joyning to the Church; not denying, that being once regularly joyned, they may after have their ſeed Baptized, though they ſhould not approve themſelves to be true Converts.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Objections</hi> and <hi>Anſwers</hi> here brought in, they are not the Objections of the Synod: And what is any way pertinent to our Diſpute, may ſufficiently be taken off by what is ſaid, and therefore I ſhall paſs them by. And I may the rather ſo do, ſeeing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:191784:16"/>our Brethren in their third Anſwer have yielded the Cauſe. For, if the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the Circumciſion of his ſeed, was appointed upon the ſame terms that Baptiſm was; Why ſhould not Baptiſm be continued ſucceſſively to the ſeed remaining in the Covenant, as well as Circumciſion?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Concerning our Brethrens Notes upon the firſt and ſecond Propoſition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the firſt Propoſition our Brethren onely give an Explication of the word <hi>Viſible Church,</hi> taking the word <hi>Church</hi> as a <hi>Genus</hi> of all particular Churches; from which we Diſſent not.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Propoſition, <hi>viz. That the Members of the viſible Church according to Scripture, are confederate viſible Believers, and their Infant-ſeed:</hi> They have made divers Notes upon it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <q>
                     <hi>That by viſible Believers, they intend true Believers to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of charity.</hi>
                  </q> And herein we agree.</p>
               <p>Second Note, <q>
                     <hi>That viſible Believers, and their Infant-ſeed, are rightly diſtinguiſhed.</hi>
                  </q> And ſo farre we agree alſo, That they are perſons diſtinctly and ſeverally covenanted with by the Lord, not <hi>wrapped up in their Parents</hi> (as they ſpeak.)</p>
               <p>But whereas they diſtinguiſh them from their Parents, <q>
                     <hi>as not being Believers, never ſo called in Scripture. How can they believe that know not the right hand from the left? They have no Faith actual or habitual, nor can have, without a Miracle, and we hold Miracles are ceaſed.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is the great Objection of the Anabaptiſts againſt the Baptizing of Infants; and what the ſcope of this Note is here, I know not, except it be to deny them any actual and perſonal Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip in the Church, as in their next Note: I ſhall therefore ſpeak
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:191784:16"/>the more fully to it. And firſt it appeareth, the Scripture numbers them amongſt Believers, if it doth not alſo expreſly call them ſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.6. <hi>One of theſe little ones that believe in me;</hi> which ſome interpret of <hi>Infants.</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14, 15. where all in the Church are called <hi>Believers,</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>Infidels:</hi> And no doubt <hi>Paul</hi> would not allow any of theſe to marry with Infidels when grown up, by that Rule of his, and therefore he reckons them as Believers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To make a perſon a Member of the viſible Church, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not whether he hath Faith and Grace really, or not; if he hath ſuch qualifications as the Rule of the Word accepteth for Faith in the viſible Church, we can go no further. This is clear, and will be eaſily granted in reſpect of adult perſons. If a man profeſs he <hi>doth believe with all his heart,</hi> as the Eunuch, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. and nothing appears to the contrary: If a man appear <hi>Pricked at the heart, Gladly receive the Word,</hi> &amp;c. as thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> 2. Gods Rule accepts of ſuch as Believers, and ſo muſt the Church, though the Lord ſeeth that ſome, it may be many ſuch, have no Faith in truth; for, <hi>Many are called, but few choſen.</hi> And however they may afterward diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves, as <hi>Ananias, Simon Magus,</hi> &amp;c. yet all will grant theſe were rightly received as viſible Believers. In like manner is the caſe of Infants: The matter is not, whether they have true Faith, or not, in the act or habit, ſo they have ſuch qualifications as God accepts of, to receive their perſons into his Covenant, and to be Members of the Body of Chriſt: This ſufficeth, though they have no Faith or Grace really. Now that the Lord doth ſo accept of them into the number of the Faithful, and as Believers, appeareth, 1. Becauſe he doth account them Holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. be it Foederal or Covenant-Holineſs, this implies that <hi>God is their God;</hi> and if God gives himſelf unto them, ſurely he accepted them as Believers: He is not the God of Infidels, who are <hi>without God,</hi> Epheſ. 2.12. The Covenant of God is the ſame with Parents and their ſeed, and therefore God accepteth them as ſuch as are anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Terms and Conditions of that Covenant. 2. This appeareth from the Nature of the Seal of the Covenant: Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was <hi>a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith,</hi> Rom. 4. When God appointed this Seal to be ſet upon Infants, ſurely God numbred
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:191784:17"/>them with Believers. So when we are ſaid to be <hi>Baptized into Chriſt,</hi> can there be any Union with Chriſt without Faith? As no real Union without true Faith, ſo no viſible Union without that which is accepted as Faith: And when the Lord Jeſus ſaith, <hi>Of ſuch is the Kingdome of God;</hi> doth the Kingdome of God belong to Unbelievers? If it be ſaid, <hi>It is their Parents Faith that is accepted for them, not any thing in their own perſons:</hi> I anſwer, If ſo, that God will accept the Parents Faith and Profeſſion in their name and ſtead, as a Publick Perſon covenanting for them; yet this is Gods free and preventing Grace towards the ſeed and doth engage their perſons to the Duties of the Covenant, to avouch <hi>God for their God,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore they are actually and perſonally in Covenant with God, as well as their Parents.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I adde further, That as we muſt reſt in ſuch Signs of Faith as the Rule requireth, though it ſhould not be there; ſo alſo we muſt in charity judge the beſt, and walk towards ſuch as viſible Believers, till by impenitency in ſin the Church have juſt cauſe to count them as <hi>Heathens and Publicans.</hi> So <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.7. <hi>It is meet I ſhould think thus of you all, becauſe you are in my heart.</hi> Love and Church-charity ſhould reach farre, eſpecially to Members of a Church regularly received, becauſe the Lord doth give Faith to ſome; and who have Faith in truth, who not, is hard for us to judge. And ſo it is in ſuch Members as came in in their Infancy: We know the Lord gives Faith and Grace to ſome betimes, as to <hi>Samuel, Timothy,</hi> and others; yea, in all Elect Infants that die in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority, no doubt God gives them the Spirit of Faith, and that which is proportionable to the act of Faith; and therefore in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we are to look at them as Believers, till for impenitency in ſin, the Church ſhall <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ount them as Heathens and Publicans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their third Note is, <q>
                     <hi>That though they be Members in general, yet Infant-ſeed are onely foederally holy; others that have taken hold of the Covenant, are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.11. <hi>Theſe have a Parental and partial Right, nor compleat and perfect. Thus the Lord ſpeaks</hi> Deut. 4 37. &amp; 10.15. Acts 2.38, 39. <hi>So Dr.</hi> Ames <hi>diſtinction into Perfect and Imperfect,</hi> Medul. Lib. 1. Cap. 32. Sect. 13.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:191784:17"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Let it here be applied what was ſaid of their Faith in Gods acceptance, and the reality of it in ſome of them, as well as in ſome admitted by Profeſſion of Faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Concerning this diſtinction of <hi>Foederal Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> It is not ſufficiently conſidered what is contained in <hi>Foederal Holineſs;</hi> Doth it not include, that <hi>They are in Covenant with God,</hi> that <hi>God is their God,</hi> that <hi>They are his People, An holy People to himſelf, A Royal Prieſthood, A Choſen Generation,</hi> &amp;c? which the Apoſtle applieth to <hi>Believers,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.9. And what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is there between <hi>Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and <hi>Saints, and Faithful in Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> which the Apoſtle attributeth to the whole Church, <hi>1 Cor.</hi> 1.2. whereof the <hi>holy ſeed</hi> was a part, <hi>1 Cor.</hi> 7.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To ſay, <hi>Theſe have Parental and partial Right,</hi> Deut. 4.37. &amp; 10.15. Acts 2.38. doth any of theſe Texts prove, that <hi>Parental Right</hi> (as they call it) or the Right by the Covenant of God with their Fathers, is <hi>a partial Right?</hi> If <hi>God loved their fathers, and therefore choſe their ſeed after them;</hi> was not the <hi>feed</hi> the object of Gods choyce? and as <hi>perfect Members</hi> of the Church in all ages, as their Fathers were? It ſeems the Lord did as great things for them, as for their Fathers, out of his love to them, bringing <hi>them out of Egypt with great power,</hi> Deut. 4.37, 38. And were not <hi>their little ones eſtabliſhed to be a People to God,</hi> as well as their Fathers? <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.11, 13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Doctor <hi>Ames</hi> makes nothing for their Tenent, but agreeth with the Synod. His ſaying (take it intire) is this: <hi>Children of the faithful are to be numbred amongst the faithful, as Members of the Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. <hi>for they are partakers of the ſame Covenant, and alſo of the ſame Profeſſion with their Parents: yet Infants are not ſo perfect Members of the Church, that they can exerciſe acts of Communion, or be admitted to partake of all Priviledges, untill the increaſe of Faith appeareth; but from thoſe things that pertain to the beginning of Faith, and entrance into the Church, they are not to be excluded.</hi> Medul. Lib. 1. Cap. 32. Sect. 12.13. By this it is evident, that he doth not make them <hi>Imperfect Members,</hi> in reſpect of the relation of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip, but in reſpect of <hi>acts of Communion:</hi> Even as a childe of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:191784:18"/>the family is not ſo perfect to do the work, &amp; enjoy all the Priviledges of the Family, as a grown perſon is; but yet he is as perfectly a Member of the Family, as a grown man. Beſides, that eminent Doctor looked at <hi>Infants of the faithful</hi> as capable of ſuch things as belong to <hi>the beginning of Faith,</hi> and to <hi>be admitted to acts of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, as the increaſe of their Faith appeareth:</hi> He thought of no other and new Memberſhip to intitle them to all Ordinances, but that, <hi>to come to them by their Covenant in Infancy.</hi> What can be more full, to ſhew his concurrence with the Synod?</p>
               <p>Object. <q>
                     <hi>But Memberſhip is a word of Relation, and therefore cannot admit of degrees of more or leſs.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To this our Brethren Anſwer, <q>
                     <hi>That it is a clear exception from the general Rule, That ſuch Relations, the foundation whereof is Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Action, do admit of diverſity of degrees; as Similitude is a Relation grounded on ſome Quality; one thing may be more or leſs like another: ſo Calefaction,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The Authors of this Diſtinction are not ſo authentick, but that it may be examined by the Rules of right Reaſon. And firſt it confoundeth all Logical Arguments, making <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Effect,</hi> yea <hi>comparata,</hi> to be <hi>Relates,</hi> which is againſt Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Diſtinction will not hold: For, what <hi>Relates</hi> are there, whoſe foundation is not in Action or Quality? Why is this man a Father, but becauſe he begat a Son? The Relation of Maſter and Servant, Husband and Wife, and the like, is it not by Covenant, which is an <hi>Action?</hi> So that by this Rule, all <hi>Relates</hi> ſhould admit <hi>Degrees of more or leſs;</hi> which is againſt that received Rule of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians.</p>
               <p>But how is this Exception applied to this caſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>In both which reſpects</hi> (ſay our Brethren) <hi>the Memberſhip of the Infants Faith, and act of Confederation being grounded on the Parents Faith, is rightly diſtinguiſhed from the Memberſhip of ſuch as are adult, which is grounded on their own Faith and Confederation.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> What dependance hath this upon the former Diſtinction? where this Relation is ſaid to be founded upon ſuch diverſity of Action, as makes two ſorts of diſtinct Members, as is pretended, and not onely two degrees of Memberſhip?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:191784:18"/> 2. There is no ſuch diverſity of the Foundation of Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as ſhould thus diſtinguiſh theſe Members; the Foundation is one and the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> The Free-grace of God in his Covenant, extended both to Parent and Childe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 9. <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed:</hi> The way of entring into this Covenant on man's part, is onely a differing <hi>modus</hi> or manner of Covenanting with God. As a Sciens put into the Stock by hand, and the Branches that grow out of it, are all equally parts of the Tree, though the Branches were not ſo put in by hand as the Sciens was. A Father that purchaſeth Lands to himſelf and his Childe, the Childe hath as perfect and good a Right as the Father hath, though he did not make the Bargain and Covenant, as his Father did.</p>
               <p>The fourth Note of our Brethren is upon thoſe words, <q>
                     <hi>Whoſe next Parents are in Covenant:</hi>
                  </q> which they ſay is <hi>ambiguous;</hi> and therefore they diſtinguiſh between <q>
                     <hi>Parental Covenant,</hi> (as they call it) <hi>and Perſonal with preſuppoſed Faith and Repentance: the former they count inſufficient to capacitate the next ſeed to Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Before I come to Anſwer their Reaſons interwoven in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: Seeing our Brethren have ſo oft recourſe to their Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Members into <hi>actual, not actual; perſonal, not perſonal;</hi> by <hi>Parental Covenant, and perſonal; immediate, and mediate; perfect, and imperfect:</hi> and lay ſo much weight upon them; as, <hi>That the Parental Covenant cannot capacitate their ſeed to Baptiſm; That their Memberſhip by Parental Covenant laſts no longer then minority,</hi> pag. 37. and, <hi>The perſonal Covenant of ſuch, makes them Members; is the Form of their Memberſhip,</hi> and the like: I ſhall therefore here, once for all, recall theſe things to <hi>the Law and Teſtimony,</hi> and try what Light is in them.</p>
               <p>And firſt, in my beſt Obſervation, I can finde no ſuch diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Parental and Perſonal Covenant,</hi> that ſhould make two ſorts or kindes of Members, neither in the Name or Thing: but all along in the Scripture, the Covenant is one and the ſame that God makes with his People, and is called by the name of <hi>Gods Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17. where this Covenant was moſt ſolemnly made, and to which the oft-renewed Covenants in the Old Teſtament, and the Covenant or Promiſe in the New Teſtament, hath reference, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:191784:19"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. In that place, I ſay, the Lord calleth it <hi>My Covenant,</hi> ſeven times, and that in reſpect of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, as well as of himſelf, <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 9, 10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12. <hi>The little ones ſtood to enter into Covenant with the Lord their God.</hi> Ezek. 16.8. <hi>I entred into Covenant with thee, and thou becameſt mine.</hi> This is the common language of the Scripture. In the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beſides other places, note that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12, 13. where the Apoſtle proves that the Church is <hi>one Body,</hi> conſiſting of <hi>many Members</hi> (ſome weak, and of leſs honour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) By Baptiſm, <hi>the Seal of the covenant,</hi> we are <hi>all Baptized into one Body;</hi> and ſo as that there might be <hi>no Schiſm in the Body:</hi> But how ſhall the <hi>Body be one,</hi> if ſome be Baptized into this Body <hi>as actual and perſonal Members,</hi> ſome <hi>not actual nor perſonal;</hi> ſome into <hi>a parental covenant,</hi> ſome <hi>perſonal?</hi> What a Schiſm might this make? ſome ſaying, <hi>I am not actually of the Body,</hi> though Baptized with the ſame Baptiſm, (and <hi>there is but one Baptiſm;</hi>) others may ſay, <hi>I am of the Body perſonally, You are no actual Members of it?</hi> It ſeemeth the Apoſtle knew not theſe Diſtinctions: So <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27, 28. <hi>All are Baptized into Chriſt, and are all one in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. I finde, that the Scripture doth clearly own the Church-ſeed grown up to adult age, to be in Covenant with God, and ſo Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church by virtue of Gods Covenant made with them in their Infancy, and that before any <hi>perſonal Covenant,</hi> as they call it. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>The Lord our God made a covenant with us in Horeb. The Lord made not this covenant with our fathers, but with us; even us, who are all of us here alive this day.</hi> Now who were theſe, but that generation numbred by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Eleazar,</hi> when all that were numbred at the firſt, of twenty years old and upward, were dead? See <hi>Numb.</hi> 26.63, 64. with <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.3. So that multitudes of theſe now alive, were in their infancy and minority when God made that Covenant with them in <hi>Horeb;</hi> and yet it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>God made that Covenant with them, even with their own perſons:</hi> that was a <hi>Perſonal,</hi> not a <hi>Parental Covenant,</hi> as our Brethren phraſe it. And this is ſet out with a double Emphaſis: 1. Negatively, <hi>Not with our fathers;</hi> Why ſo, was it not made with their fathers now dead? Yes ſurely, but not <hi>onely with them;</hi> or, <hi>not with us as wrapped up with,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:191784:19"/>or in our fathers.</hi> 2. <hi>With us,</hi> Affirmatively; and again, <hi>Even with us;</hi> and a third time, <hi>With us that are now alive,</hi> in diſtinction from <hi>their fathers that were dead:</hi> and all this before that ſecond Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. for this is ſaid of them before the Repetition of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant at <hi>Horeb,</hi> to provoke them to the obedience thereof. Where then is this <hi>Parental Covenant</hi> diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Perſonal,</hi> ſo as to make two ſorts or degrees of Members?</p>
               <p n="3">3. I obſerve, That when the Scripture calleth this Covenant, <hi>The Covenant of their fathers,</hi> or <hi>of the Lord God of their fathers,</hi> it is never ſo ſtyled, to the diminution or abatement of any Bleſſing, Priviledge, or Favour that might come to their ſeed by it, but rather for the advantage, and greater good of the Children: See <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.15, 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.3, 4, 5. <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.44, 45. <hi>I will not abhor them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But I will for their ſakes remember the covenant of their Anceſtors, whom I brought out of Egypt:</hi> So <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.31. So that in theſe, and divers other Scriptures, we ſee no ſuch diſadvantage to the ſeed, by being under <hi>Parental Covenant,</hi> as our Brethren call it; who firſt bring down Gods Covenant to a <hi>Parental Covenant,</hi> and then make a very ſlight matter of that alſo; that <hi>it cannot capacitate their ſeed to Baptiſm; Is not ſufficient to eſtabliſh their ſeed to be a people to God; Will not reach beyond the minority of their ſeed,</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>Object. But it will be Objected, <hi>That although theſe Diſtinctions be not ſo expreſly found in Scripture-phraſe, yet the nature of the ſubject doth admit ſuch Diſtinctions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Some of them cannot conſiſt with the nature of the ſubject; as for a perſon to be a Member, but not <hi>actually;</hi> a perſon in Covenant baptized into the Body of Chriſt, and yet not <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally:</hi> theſe are plain Contradictions <hi>in adjecto,</hi> as we ſay, To be <hi>A Member,</hi> and yet <hi>No Member.</hi> As for this of <hi>Parental</hi> and <hi>Perſonal Covenant,</hi> ſo much uſed, it maketh not two Covenants, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is but one, and that <hi>Gods Covenant,</hi> as is ſaid: there is but a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering <hi>modus,</hi> or manner of entring into it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for the reſt, of <hi>Mediate</hi> and <hi>Immediate Members, Perfect</hi> and <hi>Imperfect,</hi> and the reſt: Suppoſe that in ſome ſenſe the ſubject do admit them, yet they can never bear up ſuch Conſequences as are built upon them: for, they are but diſtributions <hi>ex adjunctis,</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:191784:20"/>thoſe common Adjuncts to many other Subjects, which cannot make any eſſential difference: As when we diſtinguiſh the Church into <hi>Viſible</hi> and <hi>Inviſible,</hi> it is ſtill but one and the ſame Church: So Church-Covenant into <hi>Explicite</hi> and <hi>Implicite,</hi> there is ſtill but one ſort of Churches or Covenants: So the Church is either <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compleat,</hi> without Officers, or <hi>Compleat,</hi> with her Officers; yet ſtill a true Church, and not two ſorts of Churches. Such is this caſe, if we put twenty ſuch Diſtinctions upon Members from common Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncts, they make no eſſential difference. Theſe things, beſides much more that might be ſaid, to me afford this Concluſion, That in theſe Diſtinctions, and the Conſequences thereof, there is no Scripture-Light, but a Miſt to darken the Free and Rich Grace of God, ſhining out in his Covenant to the Faithful and their ſeed.</p>
               <p>I return now to conſider the Reaſons of our Brethren, to prove, that <hi>Parental Covenant cannot capacitate their ſeed for Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their firſt Reaſon is, <q>
                     <hi>For ſo the Covenant ſhould be intailed to a thouſand generations.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> What our Brethrens <hi>Parental Covenant</hi> can do, I know not, but ſurely Gods Covenant is <hi>An everlaſting Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17.7. <hi>to be a God to their ſeed,</hi> viz. They keeping within the Covenant, <hi>from generation to generation:</hi> And if the Lord will intall his Covenant, and the Means of Grace thereby, <hi>to ſuch as keep his Covenant, to a thouſand generations,</hi> what hurt is in that? Bleſſed be his Name for it.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 2. <q>Iſhmael <hi>and</hi> Eſau <hi>had the Parental Covenant, but were not Eſtabliſhed thereby.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This was not from any inſufficiency in Gods Covenant (for ſo I muſt call it) but from their ſin that continued not in it. By this Reaſon, <hi>Perſonal Covenant by Profeſſion of Faith and Repentance,</hi> is as inſufficient; for ſuch, by their ſin, may not be eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 3. <q>
                     <hi>The immediate Parents <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief breaks off the Covenant from their ſeed,</hi> Rom. 11.20, 21, 22.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> True; ſuch Unbelief whereby they obſtinately rejected Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45, 46. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.42, 43. but this was not from any inſufficiency in Gods Covenant to <hi>capacitate their ſeed to Baptiſm,</hi> or <hi>Eſtabliſh a People,</hi> but from their rejecting of the Covenant,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:191784:20"/>in <hi>rejecting Chriſt, that Seed in whom all were to be bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reaſ. 4. <q>
                     <hi>Baptiſm is, as Circumciſion was, A Seal of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Faith,</hi> Rom. 4.11. <hi>which is inviſible in thoſe children that ſhould tranſmit Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is true, that as Circumciſion, ſo Baptiſm is <hi>a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith:</hi> And thence I infer, that when God by his Inſtitution appointed that Seal to be tranſmitted to the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo long as they continued in the viſible Covenant, they were accepted of God as Believers in Eccleſiaſtical account: and ſo it is in reſpect of tranſmitting Baptiſm; ſo long as the ſeed of the Faithful continue in the viſible Church, they are viſible Believers in Eccleſiaſtical account, and may ſo tranſmit Baptiſm to their ſeed.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 5. They alledge <q>
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. <hi>which,</hi> they ſay, <hi>reſtrains Baptiſm to the next ſeed of ſuch Parents as manifeſt Repentance and Effectual calling, and is of more weight then any Argument from far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetched and uncertain conſequences out of the Old Teſtament.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this Text is fully anſwered before; and, as was ſaid, it favours the Doctrine of the Synod, <hi>That the Promiſe or Covenant is the ground of Baptiſm.</hi> And that this Text hath no ſuch <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> it may appear thus: Let all be granted that is here ſaid, yet ſuppoſe ſuch viſible Converts diſcover afterward no ſap or ſavour of Grace, to the faireſt Charity, but continue ſtill in the Church, ſhall not their ſeed be Baptized? or muſt every Church-member hold forth a Profeſſion of Repentance at the Baptiſm of every childe? I ſuppoſe our Brethren will not ſo affirm; and if ſo, then a Church-member, though not apparently a true Penitent, may have his ſeed Baptized. As for <hi>far-fetched Conſequences from the Old Teſtament,</hi> the following Diſcourſe will ſhew, that none uſe them ſo much as our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren do.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Anſwers here given to an Objection from <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. The Synod doth not make that Objection, but agreeth with this Interpretation given in the third and fourth Anſwer; <hi>viz. So that the Priviledges are onely continued to the ſeed of the next Parents, that continue in the Covenant, and are not broken off.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:191784:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Concerning the third Propoſition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Propoſ 3. <hi>THat the Infant-ſeed of Confederate viſible Believers, are Members of the ſame Church with their Parents, and when grown up, are perſonally under the Watch and Government of that Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Diſſenting Brethren, by their dilute interpretations of this Propoſition, ſeem to recede from their own Conceſſions: For this Propoſition was propounded, and earneſtly promoted by one of the chief of them, as tending to iſſue other Difficulties amongſt us, and to <hi>Reform the corruptions of Youth:</hi> and there were not above three noted that diſſented from it. But when it was obſerved (as is here ſaid) that the other Propoſitions would be inferred from it, and ſo ſtrongly, that ſome ſaid, <hi>The whole Cauſe was given up in that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition;</hi> Our Brethren therefore now think to eaſe the matter by their interpretations: but ſuch they are, as cannot conſiſt with the terms of the Propoſition, as will appear.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> (ſay they) <hi>when it is ſaid, They are perſonally under the Watch of the Church; the meaning is not, that they have an actual, perſonal, and immediate Memberſhip, which is proper to thoſe in full communion, but onely that the Church-watch, in the diſpenſation of it, ſhould reach unto their perſons: which was publickly expreſſed in the Meeting-houſe by us.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> How inconſiſtent are theſe things? 1. Theſe perſons are <hi>Members of the Church,</hi> but not <hi>actually:</hi> How then are they Members? <hi>potentially?</hi> ſo are many that are fit matter for a Church, that yet are no Members: or are they ſo <hi>habitually?</hi> ſurely they are actually <hi>Baptized into the Body of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.13. And ſhall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:191784:21"/>we Baptize actually, ſuch as are not actually in the Covenant? 2. <hi>They are perſonally under the Watch and Government of the Church,</hi> yet the Church muſt not deal with their perſons, but reach their perſons at the ſecond hand, <hi>viz.</hi> by their Parents: (So indeed ſome expreſſed themſelves, but I thought it would not have been owned by the reſt) But <hi>thus to reach their perſons,</hi> is not to touch them with any act of Church-government, but of Family-government onely. Yea, thus to <hi>reach their perſons,</hi> is no more then the Church may reach an Heathen ſervant: for the Church may Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Maſter, if he reſtrain not the evils of his Servant, as well as a Father for the evils of his Childe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> (ſay they) <hi>By Diſcipline, we do not intend Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which is proper to Offenders in full communion; for how can they be caſt out of full communion that were never in it?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Then they muſt ſuppoſe that Excommunication is no part of Diſcipline, or intend a Diſcipline ineffectual to Chriſts ends: for what are Admonitions unregarded, without that Cenſure to ſet them home? <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. Excommunication is not to caſt out of full communion onely, but out of all communion: <hi>Let him be as an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and Publican.</hi> It is a giving up <hi>to Satan, for the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the Spirit may be ſaved,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.5. and this ſoveraign Medicine all that are within are capable of, and may ſtand in need of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Nevertheleſs,</hi> ſay they, <hi>the Church may diſown them, and declare them to be no Members, upon their deſerting of the Church, and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of their fathers, by ſuch a Sentence as</hi> Peter <hi>pronounced to</hi> Simon Magus, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.21.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. This diſowning ſuch as no Members, is a meer inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of man, never ordained of Chriſt, nor tending to reach the ends of his Diſcipline: for, though it ſeems to agree with Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in not owning them as Members; yet it wanteth that aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dread of Excommunication, to humble the ſinner, and bring him in. Yea, thus to diſown them as no Members, is to rid the Church of any further care of them, as thoſe <hi>without.</hi> But all acts of Chriſts Diſcipline, are acts of the love and compaſſion of Chriſt and his Church to the Souls of offenders, to ſeek their Repentance and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:191784:22"/>Salvation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.21. giveth no ground of this Practice: For, 1. <hi>Peter</hi> did not preſently diſown him as no Member (neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed doth the place referre to Memberſhip, but to <hi>the power of giving the Holy Ghoſt</hi>) but declaring his ſin and danger, he exhorteth him to <hi>Repentance,</hi> and to <hi>pray to God for pardon,</hi> ver. 22. which implies, that upon his Repentance he was ready to promiſe pardon, according to the end of Chriſts Diſcipline: but perſiſting impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently in his ſin, he might then be <hi>caſt out.</hi> Beſides, 2. This Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was upon one that came in by <hi>Profeſſion of Faith;</hi> and if that were <hi>Peters</hi> meaning, to diſown him as no Member of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, and it be an Example to be imitated, then any Member diſcovering Hypocrifie to a diſcerning Spirit, might preſently be diſowned as no Member, which would make ſad work in Churches. 3. If the Church may diſown them, when they deſert the Church and Covenant, then they may, yea ought to own them as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, when they <hi>own the Covenant,</hi> and do not deſert the Church.</p>
               <p>I cannot but make a little pauſe here, before I paſs on; and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly intreat our dear Brethren, and all of their minde, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well how the Lord is wont to deal with his viſible Church, and all the Members thereof, in the Old and New Teſtament, and compare therewith this their reſpect and care of <hi>the Lambs of Chriſts Flock.</hi> When the Lord hath once ſtricken <hi>a Covenant with his People,</hi> taking in <hi>their ſeed</hi> with the Parents, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What <hi>Abundant Means of their Salvation</hi> doth he ordain, and cauſe diligently to be improved to that end? <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> both admitted to Sacrifice; <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Commands were <hi>to his whole Family-Church,</hi> Gen. 18. The <hi>daily ordinary Sacrifices,</hi> and the more <hi>ſolemn and extraordinary,</hi> were for <hi>the whole Congregation,</hi> Lev. 4.14, 21. Numb. 15.24, 25. <hi>To Iſrael pertain the Adoption, the Glory, and the Covenants, and the giving of the Law, and the Service of God, and the Promiſes,</hi> Rom. 94. And how did the Lord follow his Church in all ages by his Prophets, to bring them to Repentance? yea, when gone after <hi>Baal,</hi> to reduce them by <hi>Elijah.</hi> How affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately doth the Lord by them plead with his People? <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:191784:22"/>
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Micah</hi> 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.8, &amp;c. So in the New Teſtament, the <hi>Miniſtry of the Word,</hi> and other <hi>Ordinances,</hi> are given to the <hi>Viſible Church for their Salvation,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.28. Epheſ. 4.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> to reduce and ſave offenders.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider the <hi>Wonderfull Patience of God</hi> in ſeeking the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his viſible Church. When the <hi>children of God were ſo corrupt,</hi> that God reſolved <hi>to deſtroy all fleſh;</hi> yet he ſpared them <hi>an hundred and twenty years,</hi> ſending <hi>Noah a Preacher of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to ſeek their good, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 6. And how great was his Patience to <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah, ſending his Prophets early and late,</hi> out of his compaſſion, <hi>till there was no remedy?</hi> 2 Chron. 36. So the Lord Jeſus ſent his Epiſtles <hi>To the ſeven Churches of Aſia,</hi> to heal their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions; and though he threatned to <hi>Come quickly,</hi> yet ſpared them many years.</p>
               <p n="3">3. See with what <hi>Compaſſion and Bowels,</hi> of humane Affections, as it were, <hi>the Lord expreſſeth himſelf,</hi> when he is about to caſt off a People he hath been in Covenant with: <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, O Ephraim?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>my Repentings are kindled together,</hi> Hoſ. 11.8. So Chriſt, <hi>O Jeruſalem, how oft would I have gathered thee, as an Hen her Chickens?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37. How did he <hi>Weepover Jeruſalem, ſaying, O that thou hadst known at leaſt in this thy day!</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41. This is Gods way. But what is our <hi>Brethrens Way</hi> to theſe Members of the viſible Church, to whom they confeſs <hi>the Promiſe doth belong?</hi> Acts 2.39.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Though God have ſtricken his Covenant with them, and Sealed it <hi>To be their God,</hi> and own them to be <hi>His People;</hi> yet they will not acknowledge them <hi>Actual perſonal Members,</hi> but in effect <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them out of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They allow them no more acts of <hi>Church-watch and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> then may reach an Infidel-ſervant: and <hi>Excommunication,</hi> the moſt effectual Ordinance of Chriſt to <hi>Deſtroy the Fleſh, and Save the Soul,</hi> muſt not touch them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So quick they are, that if the Lord be not pleaſed to give them <hi>Saving Faith and Grace ſo ſoon as they come to adult age,</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own them as <hi>No Members,</hi> and ſo let them go. Now how farre unlike this is to <hi>Gods Way,</hi> who doth not ſee? And I muſt confeſs
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:191784:23"/>this is to me one great Argument, That the <hi>Way of theſe Brethren</hi> is not the <hi>Way of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To proceed: Our Brethren to clear this Coaſt, think fit to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <hi>The Reaſons of the Synod to prove their Continuance in the Church.</hi> But the Reader muſt note, That thoſe Arguments are not applied to this Propoſition in hand, here being <hi>Eight Reaſons</hi> to prove <hi>They are perſonally under the Watch and Diſcipline of the Church,</hi> which are not touched by them. But the <hi>Reaſons</hi> that our Brethren here ſpeak unto, are thoſe brought by the Synod to prove the laſt Branch of the ſixth Argument for the fifth Propoſition, <hi>viz. That Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members admitted in minority, underſtanding the Doctrine of Faith, and publickly profeſſing their Aſſent thereto; not ſcandalous in life, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly owning the Covenant before the Church, wherein they give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and children to the Lord, and ſubject themſelves to the Government of Chriſt in the Church; That their Memberſhip ſtill continueth in adult age, and ceaſeth not with their Infancy.</hi> And this is the rather to be noted, becauſe if their Anſwers ſuit not the caſe of ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, then they are not pertinent to take off the Reaſons of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. But let us ſee what is anſwered to theſe Reaſons (though out of their place.)</p>
               <q>Reaſ. 1. <hi>Becauſe in Scripture perſons are broken off onely for notorious ſins, or incorrigible impenitency and unbelief; not for growing up to adult age,</hi> Rom 11.20.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Our Brethren anſwer, <q>
                     <hi>Not ſimply for growing up, but for ſuch acceſſaries as may attend adult age.</hi> Rom. 11.20. <hi>doth not ſay onely for notorious ſins,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Negative unbelief, Neglecting the means of Grace, Not Profeſſing the Faith, and the fruits thereof, may give cauſe of breaking off. And to ſuch, though our patience and expectation ought to be large and long, yet it may be tired out at laſt, and come to a period.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. If our Brethren would out hold to this, it would tend much to our deſired Unity. For, hence it will follow. That their Memberſhip received in infancy doth continue in adult age, untill ſuch <hi>Acceſſaries</hi> do appear, and till the <hi>Patience of the Church be tired out.</hi> 2. If it were granted that <hi>Negative unbelief,</hi> manifeſted by <hi>Neglect of the means of Grace, Not profeſſing of the Faith, and the fruits thereof,</hi> might, after long patience, give juſt cauſe to break them
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:191784:23"/>off; yet, by this Rule, the perſons deſcribed in the fifth Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot be ſaid to be <hi>broken off,</hi> for they do <hi>Profeſs the Faith, and the fruits thereof,</hi> by a life free from Scandal, <hi>giving up themſelves to God,</hi> and <hi>ſubmitting to the Government of Chriſt in his Church:</hi> Or at leaſt ſuch as theſe are ſtill objects of the Churches <hi>Patience,</hi> and therefore not <hi>broken off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing our Brethren come thus farre, I ſhall willingly meet them here, and confeſs, That if <hi>Negative unbelief</hi> be manifeſted by <hi>Neglect of the means of Grace, Not profeſſing of the Faith</hi> (being or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly called thereunto by the Church) and <hi>Continuance impen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tently in ſuch Neglects, after due means, with due patience uſed by the Church,</hi> this would give the Church juſt cauſe to caſt them out for this were <hi>Incorrigible Impenitency in ſin.</hi> And, Oh that we might meet here! But when I conſider many other Expreſſions in this Treatiſe, I fear my deſires will fail: For, if no act of Church-governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t may be put forth upon their perſons <hi>immediately,</hi> but by their Parents, how ſhall the Church come at them, to put them upon ſuch Duties, and deal with them for their Neglect thereof? and when their Parents be dead, what ſhall the Church do then? and when their Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is owned onely in general, as <hi>wrapped up in their Parents,</hi> not <hi>actual</hi> or <hi>perſonal;</hi> yea, when their <hi>Perſonal</hi> or <hi>Foederal Holineſs</hi> is denied to continue in adult age? Theſe, and the like Paſſages, <hi>Pag.</hi> 23, 25, 37. and in other places, do make me fear, that our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren will not hold to their Expreſſions in this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply</hi> 2. Although <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. ſaith, <hi>Not onely for notorious ſins,</hi> &amp;c. yet it ſheweth how the Jews were broken off, which we know was for <hi>Notorious ſins,</hi> and <hi>Incorrigible Impenitency,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief.</hi> And let any ſhew, that any have been <hi>broken off,</hi> or by Rule may be ſo, for <hi>Negative unbelief,</hi> without <hi>Impenitency</hi> added. The contrary we finde 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.43. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45, 46. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.8.</p>
               <q>Reaſ. 2. <hi>The Jewiſh children circumciſed, did not ceaſe to be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers by growing up to adult age, but continued in the Church, and were bound to the Duties of Members,</hi> Deut. 26.2-10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.16-17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 53.</q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>The circumciſed Jews did not ceaſe to be Members ſimply for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:191784:24"/>growing up, but for growing out of kinde.</hi> Jer. 2.21. <hi>They became de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Plants.</hi> Amos 9.7. <hi>Children of the Negroes; Baſtard Branches to be cut off,</hi> Joh. 15.2.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> There is a double great miſtake in applying theſe Scriptures. 1. They do not ſpeak of perſons <hi>ceaſing to be Members.</hi> As for <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. it was the <hi>Word of the Lord to Jeruſalem,</hi> ver. 2. and that in <hi>the thirteenth year of Joſiah,</hi> after the Covenant was renewed, and Religion greatly Reformed; and God calls them <hi>His People,</hi> ver. 11, 13 and therefore their Memberſhip ceaſed not at that time. So <hi>Amos</hi> 9. He Propheſied <hi>in the dayes of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah King of Judah, and Joaſh the ſon of Jeroboam King of Iſrael,</hi> in whoſe dayes God had not yet <hi>removed Iſrael out of his ſight.</hi> As for <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.2. though the Lord doth in his time cut off <hi>unfruitful Branches</hi> by Death, or Church-cenſures, yet till he doth ſo, they are expreſly ſaid to be <hi>in Chriſt.</hi> So that theſe places ſpeak nothing of <hi>the ceaſing of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberſhip in adult age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe places do not ſuit the perſons in the fifth Propoſition. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. ſpeaketh of ſuch as <hi>Propheſied by Baal; That played the harlot on every high hill,</hi> ver. 20. and are therefore called <hi>A degenerate plant,</hi> ver. 21. <hi>Amos</hi> ſpeaketh of Iſrael in the corrupt times of Idolatry, and reproves their great <hi>Covetouſneſs and Oppreſſion,</hi> Chap. 8.4, 5. And therefore if ſuch as thoſe had <hi>ceaſed to be Members in adult age,</hi> it doth not follow that the Memberſhip of theſe in queſtion doth ceaſe.</p>
               <p>What is here added about the phraſe of <hi>Entring into Covenant,</hi> is a miſtake: for, the Synod ſpeaks of <hi>Entring into a new Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> not denying the phraſe of <hi>Entring into,</hi> or <hi>Renewing the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Reaſ. 3. <hi>Thoſe Relations of Bond-ſervants and Subjects, which the Scripture maketh uſe of to ſet forth the ſtate of the children of the Church by,</hi> Levit. 25.41, 42. Ezek. 37.25. <hi>do not ceaſe with Infancy, but continue in adult age, whereby they are engaged to duty when they are moſt fit for it. So here.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 1. <hi>The Relation of the Son of the Bond-woman may ceaſe in adult age, as</hi> Iſhmael; <hi>much more of the Bond-ſervant.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The Relation of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> ceaſed not by growing up to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:191784:24"/>adult age, nor till he was caſt out for his ſin. Theſe in queſtion are not <hi>caſt out,</hi> or deſerving ſo to be: and therefore this Anſwer is impertinent.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 2. <hi>By this Reaſon, Moral wickedneſs ſhould not cut off adult Members, for that doth not cut off the Relation of Bond-ſervants.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This Argument taken from the common nature of Civil and Church-Societies, doth not require they ſhould hold in all things; as, that they ſhould be governed by the ſame Laws, and ſubject to the ſame Puniſhments: that were indeed to make <hi>Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes run on all four</hi> (as we ſay.) It is enough if they agree in that thing wherein they are applied. And this Application of the Synod is clear in <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.41, 42. where the children of the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elitiſh Servants were to <hi>ſerve with their parents unto the year o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jubile,</hi> which being every Fiftieth Year, they were oft grown up to adult age before that time: And the reaſon why they ſhould then go out, is, <hi>Becauſe they</hi> (that is, Parents and Children) <hi>are my Servants, ſaith the Lord.</hi> So that there is the like reaſon in Gods Service, as in that Relation. And we ſee <hi>David</hi> delighteth to own himſelf <hi>the Servant of the Lord</hi> in this very Relation: <hi>I am thy Servant, the Son of thine Handmaid,</hi> Pſal. 116.16. that is, engaged to the Service of God from his Birth, and ſo for ever, as the Son of the Handmaid was, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.4. And yet if the Similitude ſhould be preſſed ſo farre, we know that the <hi>Moral Wickedneſs</hi> of Murther, Adultery, and the like, would cut off Servants and Subjects by Death, according to the Law of God.</p>
               <q>Reaſ. 4. <hi>There is no ordinary way of ceſſation of Church-memberſhip but by Death, Diſmiſſion, Excommunication, or Diſſolution of the Society; none of which is the caſe of the children in queſtion.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 1. <hi>This is to be underſtood of Members in full communion, which theſe adult children are not.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> If none of theſe belong to ſuch adult children, to cauſe their Memberſhip to ceaſe; then by their judgement, it ſeems, they have no Memberſhip at all, if neither <hi>Death,</hi> nor <hi>Diſſolution of the Society,</hi> can cauſe it to ceaſe: which before they ſeemed not to own.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 2. <hi>There are many other wayes of the ceſſation of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:191784:25"/>they may Excommunicate themſelves (as Mr.</hi> Cotton, <hi>The Aſſembly at the</hi> Savoy, <hi>and Dr.</hi> Ames <hi>affirm.) Alſo by Withdrawing; ſometimes commanded of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. Rom 16.17. <hi>Alſo by Apoſtacy,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.19. <hi>By Hereſie, as Arrians, Quakers,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. If theſe adult children may <hi>Excommunicate themſelves,</hi> then it is yielded that they are Members in adult age. But if all theſe were granted, yet none of them is the caſe of theſe in the fifth Propoſition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is a needleſs multiplying of particulars: All, but a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <hi>Lawful Withdrawing,</hi> are Subjects of Excommunication, as ſhall be proved. Concerning a <hi>Lawful Withdrawing,</hi> that <hi>Turning away from ſuch,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. and <hi>Avoiding thoſe,</hi> Rom. 16.17. may more fitly be underſtood to be done, by not admitting them into the Church, or caſting them out if they be in; rather then by <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from the Church it ſelf for their ſakes,</hi> which cannot be done without Schiſm, except many Cautions be uſed. Neither can ſuch <hi>Withdrawing</hi> looſen a man's Relation to the Church, which no doubt may call him to account for it, and he is bound to <hi>render a reaſon thereof;</hi> elſe all Diſcipline may hereby be made fruſtrate. Now if his <hi>Reaſons</hi> be found juſt, it will be all one with a <hi>Diſmiſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Concerning this <hi>Self-Excommunication:</hi> 1. The ordinary inſtances of <hi>Cain, Iſhmael, Eſau,</hi> are not clear that they did <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate themſelves,</hi> but were <hi>caſt out by the Lord.</hi> The Curſe of <hi>Cain,</hi> was to be <hi>A Vagabond and Fugitive in the earth;</hi> which he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of his caſting out of the Church, <hi>From thy face ſhall I be hid,</hi> Gen. 4.14. As for <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> the caſe is plain that he was caſt out by <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Governour of the Church, by the appointment of God. And of <hi>Eſau</hi> it is expreſly ſaid, that <hi>when he would have inherited the Bleſſing, he was rejected,</hi> viz. of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> after which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, he went away from the Church in <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Family. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the inſtance of <hi>the Sons of Abraham by Keturah,</hi> how long they continued to Worſhip the true God, or how they fell off, who can ſay, or prove that they <hi>Excommunicated themſelves,</hi> without any act of God that had the nature of ſuch a Cenſure? As for <hi>Open and Obſtinate Hereticks and Apoſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es:</hi> which ſome call <hi>Excommunicati de Jure,</hi> that hindreth not but that they may, and ought to be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:191784:25"/>in Fact alſo. But if we ſpeak of Goſpel-times, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Lord Jeſus hath ſo expreſly inſtituted Church-cenſures, for the ſaving of Offenders, and purging of his Churches; and hath confirmed the ſame with ſuch Promiſes, to <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nde and Looſe in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, what is Bound and Looſed on Earth,</hi> Mat. 18. I conceive (with due reſpect to the Authors alledged) That no Member of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church (having the Power and Exerciſe of Church-Diſcipline) can ſo cut off his Relation to that Church actually, but that the Church may, and ought to diſpenſe the Cenſures to him, as the caſe ſhall require. My Reaſons are:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. From the Ends of Church-Diſcipline; <hi>viz. To reduce and ſave Offenders,</hi> Mat. 18. 1 Cor. 5.5. <hi>To purge the Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.7. <hi>To vindicate the Name and Glory of God, in bearing fall teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scandals,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.14. 2 Cor. 7.11. <hi>You have approved your ſelves to be clear in this matter: For the Example and Terrour of others,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.20. Whence the Reaſon ſtands thus:</p>
               <p>If the Lord Jeſus hath betruſted his Church with the Power of Church-Diſcipline for theſe and the like Ends; then it is the duty of the Church to put forth this Power whenſoever theſe, or any of theſe ends may be attained with the Edification of the Church. But there is no caſe can befall any Church member, wherein theſe, or ſome of theſe ends may not be attained. For, put caſe a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be turned <hi>Arrian, Quaker, Turk,</hi> and what you will; yet the Cenſure denounced will <hi>Acquit the Church, Vindicate the Name and Glory of God, in bearing full teſtimony againſt ſuch Scandals,</hi> and <hi>tend to the Terrour of others:</hi> yea, who knoweth how farre the Lord may improve it upon the ſinner for his good?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. If in Scripture-patterns, the worſt of Hereticks and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers were laid under Cenſures, notwithſtanding their ſuppoſed <hi>Self-Excommunication,</hi> then we ought to follow ſuch Patterns in all ſuch caſes. But ſuch was the Practice in Scripture-examples, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. That Poſition that openeth a door for Church-members to evade and fruſtrate Church-Diſcipline, is not to be admitted. But this Poſition doth open a door to evade and fruſtrate Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. For, by this means, any Member in danger of Church-cenſures
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:191784:26"/>may <hi>Withdraw himſelf, Renounce the Church,</hi> and then they cannot proceed againſt him: for, it were in vain to cut off a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that hath already <hi>Excommunicated himſelf.</hi> If any ſhall ſay, <hi>It is ſufficient puniſhment and judgement of God, to leave a man ſo to Excommunicate himſelf. Anſ.</hi> But how then ſhall the Church be diſcharged of their duty to <hi>ſave the Offender by Excommunication,</hi> that tends <hi>to deſtroy the fleſh,</hi> and <hi>ſave his Soul?</hi> I never read that God bleſſed <hi>Self-Excommunication</hi> to that end. Yea, by this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, a wicked Schiſmatical Member ſhall take the Keyes out of the hands of the Church, and Cenſure the whole Church, (as oft they do) and the Church hath no Power to lay any Puniſhment upon him for it.</p>
               <p>And hence thoſe Scriptures alledged <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.21. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. may receive a juſt Anſwer; for, that <hi>Forſaking of the aſſembling of themſelves,</hi> and <hi>Going out,</hi> doth not exempt them from Church-cenſures, or prove that they were <hi>cut off</hi> before Church-cenſures. <hi>If the foot ſaith, I am not of the Body, is it therefore not of the Body?</hi> Or can this <hi>Withdrawing</hi> diſcharge the Church from uſing the means of their recovery, or exempt themſelves from the juſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Puniſhment appointed by Chriſt for ſuch Offenders?</p>
               <q>Reaſ. 5. <hi>Theſe adult perſons are Members or Non-members; if Non-members, then a perſon admitted a Member, and ſealed by Baptiſm, not caſt out, nor deſerving ſo to be, may (the Church ſtill remaining) become a Non-member, out of the Church, and of the unclean world: which the Scripture acknowledgeth not.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 1. <hi>Members and Non-members are not oppoſites, but with taking in the conditions of all oppoſites, as in this caſe</hi> (ad idem, <hi>or in the ſame respect) they may be Non-members in full communion, and yet Members in Parental Right.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. This Diſtinction is not <hi>ad idem;</hi> for the want of full Communion is not ſuch a reſpect as makes a man a Non-member, for ſo a man under Admonition for ſome Scandal, or in a Frenzy, ſhould be a Non-member. 2. The queſtion is not, <hi>Whether theſe be Members in full Communion?</hi> but, <hi>Whether that Memberſhip which was ſealed up unto them in Baptiſm, doth continue in adult age?</hi> And this ſeems once more here to be granted.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:191784:26"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 2. <hi>They may deſerve Cenſures, though not put upon them.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ply.</hi> This is not the caſe of theſe Members in queſtion: And if it were ſo, that they <hi>deſerved Cenſures,</hi> yet no man is actually cut off, till the Cenſure be applied. And, if <hi>they may deſerve Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> then are they Perſonal Members under Church-Diſcipline.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Concerning the fourth Propoſition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Propoſ. 4. <hi>THeſe adult perſons are not therefore to be admitted to full Communion, meerly becauſe they are, and continue Members, without ſuch further Qualifications as the Word of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Brethren granting this Propoſition, yet in reference to the fifth Propoſition, are pleaſed by way of Prevention to ſtate this Queſtion; <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Whether there are, or ſhould be in the Church, ſuch perſons as have publickly and perſonally Covenanted, that are not in full Communion?</hi>
                  </q> The Negative they prove:</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 1. <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe publick and perſonal Covenanting is the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of a Church-member; ſuch have all the conſtituent cauſes, and ſo all the conſequences of the Form, and all the priviledges of that Subject, which in this caſe is full Communion. Hence the Form introduced, and the Covenant perſonally owned, doth neceſſarily imply all the priviledges belonging<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th reunto.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Every <hi>Publick and Perſonal Covenanting is not the Form of Church-memberſhip.</hi> The Covenant was oft renewed, publickly owned, or Entred into, by ſuch as were Members of the Church before; as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. and other Scriptures, doth appear. And this is the caſe of theſe in queſtion, who were in Covenant with God and his Church, and had the <hi>Seal of Baptiſm ſet thereto</hi> before, <hi>Geneſ.</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:191784:27"/>17.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. and therefore this <hi>Owning of the Covenant,</hi> is onely a manifeſtation of their continuance in it. And hence this is not the <hi>Form of their Memberſhip,</hi> but a Duty of their Covenant, and doth not in it ſelf fit them for full Communion, except withall they hold out ſuch <hi>Qualifications as the Word of God r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quireth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi> A Youth that hath the conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuent cauſes of a Man, Soul and Body, with ſome Underſtanding and Reaſon, is not thereby capable of all Priviledges of a man; as, To Marry, Give good Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances of Lands, and the like. An adult perſon received into the Church by perſonal Covenant, is not fit for the Lords Supper meerly becauſe he hath Covenanted, for except he hath ſuitable qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he will <hi>Eat judgement to himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reaſ. 2. <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe thoſe that were admitted by perſonal Covenant in the Primitive Church, continued in full Communion,</hi> Acts 2.41.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is not the ſame reaſon; for they were admitted in adult age, and alſo indued with eminent Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt: Theſe being admitted in Infancy, do onely by <hi>Owning the Covenant,</hi> manif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt their continuance therein. The <hi>Indians</hi> newly converted, and holding forth ſo much Faith and Repentance as may admit them into the Church and Baptiſm, might yet need further Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to the Lords Supper, not having ſuch eminent gifts.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 3. <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe this Doctrine preſuppoſeth, that what Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Faith and Repentance is required in adult perſons coming to Baptiſm, is not ſufficient to the Lords Supper.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This Doctrine doth not ſuppoſe it; for it ſpeaketh onely of ſuch adult perſons as were Baptized in infancy, not to be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in adult age. It ſuppoſeth onely that perſons Baptized in infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and continuing in the Covenant, and viſible Church, may yet be unable to <hi>Examine themſelves, and diſcern the Lords Body.</hi> And hence the Reaſons which here follow, touch not this caſe. And it is well if ſome of them do not argue <hi>Againſt the Baptizing of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ants;</hi> or, <hi>That Infants Baptized may partake of the Lords Supper.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:191784:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Concerning the fifth Propoſition.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Propoſ. 5. <hi>CHurch-members who were admitted in minority, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Doctrine of Faith, and publickly profeſſing their Aſſent thereto; not ſcandalous in life, and ſolemnly owning the Covenant before the Church, wherein they give up themſelves and their children to the Lord, and ſubject themſelves to the Government of Chriſt in the Church, their children are to be Baptized.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>"This Propoſition</hi> (ſay our Brethren) <hi>doth ſtumble us moſt.</hi> Their Reaſons are:</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 1. <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe, there being three Expreſſions propounded, this ſwerveth further then the other from the Scripture.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Be it granted, that ſeveral terms and expreſſions of theſe Qualifications were propounded; theſe onely in concluſion were Aſſented unto. But if our Brethren judge, <hi>That they all ſwerved from the Scripture,</hi> what matter is it <hi>which ſwerved moſt from it?</hi> If this <hi>ſwerveth moſt,</hi> they have the more advantage of Diſpute againſt it. But ſeeing they <hi>ſtumble</hi> ſo much at this, I ſhall eaſily remove this Block out of their way.</p>
               <p>Obj. <q>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſay they, <hi>in the former Expreſſions it was required, they ſhould underſtand the Grounds of Religion; here, no more then the Doctrine of Faith: So that they may be ignorant of the Doctrine of the Moral Law, and ſo have no knowledge of Sin, of the Duties of Holineſs, Righteouſneſs, Sabbaths,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As if the <hi>Doctrine of Faith</hi> were not as large as all the <hi>Grounds of Religion,</hi> both in the acceptation of Scripture, and of Orthodox Divines. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27. when the Apoſtle exhorts them to <hi>ſtrive for the Faith of the Gospel,</hi> might they let go the Doctrine of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:191784:28"/>the Moral Law, or any other Grounds of Religion? 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>He had kept the Faith,</hi> did he let go the Doctrine of the Moral Law, and other Grounds of Religion? <hi>Jude</hi> ver. 3. <hi>Contend for the Faith;</hi> was not <hi>that Faith</hi> oppoſed to the <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y Dreamers</hi> that ſinned againſt the Moral Law? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſurely <hi>the Doctrine of Faith</hi> comprehends <hi>the Doctrine of the Moral Law.</hi> When our Synod at <hi>Cambridge</hi> 1648. declared their Conſent with the Aſſembly of Divines in <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>The Doctrine of Faith;</hi> and the Aſſembly at the <hi>Savoy</hi> calleth that Book <hi>A Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Faith and Order;</hi> do they not mean by the word <hi>Faith,</hi> all the Grounds of Religion, excepting onely matters of <hi>Order?</hi> But what need more Inſtances, when the Preface to this Book telleth the world of <hi>A few Names that are ſtedfaſt in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel?</hi> I dare not be ſo uncharitable, to think, that ſuch perſons do not hold faſt <hi>The Doctrine of the Moral Law,</hi> and all <hi>The Grounds of Religion.</hi> Surely the Synod intended it ſo.</p>
               <p>Obj. 2. <q>
                     <hi>In the ſecond Expreſſion it was required, that they ſhould be Examined of their ſenſe of their need of Chriſt, and deſires after him; here, only of their Aſſent to the Doctrine of Faith, which the Devils may have.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.</hi> But if ſuch <hi>ſenſe of their need of Chriſt, and deſires after him,</hi> ſhould not, upon ſuch Examination, appear, but this <hi>Aſſent to the Doctrine of Faith,</hi> with all the other Qualifications; Might not this ſuffice to ſhew <hi>their Continuance in the viſible Church?</hi> What if the Devils may give an <hi>Aſſent</hi> to the Truth? it is not free, but inforced; and they want all the other Qualifications, that theſe have.</p>
               <p>Obj. 3. <q>
                     <hi>The former required, that they ſhould give Satisfaction for any Offence they had fallen into; here, onely that they are not Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in life. The former,</hi> viz. <hi>Offences, comprehend Original Sin, or any other committed againſt God or man,</hi> Jam. 3 2. <hi>Scandal in lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, noteth onely Notorious ſins, and a courſe therein.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That they <hi>ſtumble</hi> at this, muſt needs ariſe from a very rigid Principle (whereof this Treatiſe hath too many) For, who ever took up that of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> as matter of offence to deal with his Brother for it? Or what Rule have we to call for <hi>Satisfaction</hi> for that, or for all ſuch Words or Actions as are <hi>Offences to God or
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:191784:28"/>man?</hi> A practice that the Apoſtle condemneth in that very place alledged, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3 1. <hi>Be not many maſters; for in many things we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend all:</hi> and therefore pity, and bear with one another and be not ſo rigid to require Satisfaction for every Offence. If this were not ſo, what uſe were there of thoſe Rules of Love, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Love beareth all things.</hi> Gal. 6.2. <hi>Bear one anothers burthens.</hi> Col. 3.13. <hi>Forbearing one another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is evident <hi>Luke</hi> 17.1, 2, 3. that Offences to be dealt with are Scandals: <hi>Woe to him that ſcandalizeth one of theſe little ones;</hi> and Impenitency in any ſuch Scandal deſerveth the higheſt Cenſure, but repented of, ceaſeth to be a Scandal or Offence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſuch a Scandal ſhould not be a notorious ſin, nor continued in but in one act: So that <hi>Not to be ſcandalous in life,</hi> is full as large as that other Expreſſion, and doth include <hi>Satisfaction for Offences that are fallen into.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj. 4. <q>
                     <hi>In the former was ſaid, They ſhould own the Covenant of their Parents; here, onely the Covenant: which may extend to Grandfathers,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I wonder how our Brethren could make to themſelves ſuch a Block as this is to <hi>ſtumble</hi> upon, when-as the Doctrine of the Synod is ſo expreſs to the contrary in the ſecond Propoſition, which affirmeth, That this right in the Covenant is conveyed onely by the <hi>next Parents,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. If men have a luſt to contend, and raiſe Objections, they might as well have objected againſt the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer phraſe, <hi>The Covenant of their Parents;</hi> for are not Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers <hi>Parents</hi> alſo?</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Theſe things</hi> (ſay our Brethren) <hi>thus weighed, may ſuffice to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, whether there be not juſt cauſe for us to deny our Conſent to ſuch kinde of Members as theſe.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But theſe things weighed over again by the equal Ballance of the Sanctuary, and right Reaſon, I doubt not but the Judicious Reader will ſee how light they are, and unworthy to ſway the Judgements of ſuch as our Brethren are. But they adde (as they had need) other Reaſons of their Deniall.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 2. <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe this croſſeth the two former Propoſitions, which make the proper Subjects of Baptiſm, Confederate viſible Believers and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:191784:29"/>their ſeed: whereas theſe, though ſo qualified, are not (neither Parents nor Children) viſible Believers; for the vileſt perſons may have theſe,</hi> Rom. 2.18. &amp; 10 19, 21. <hi>yea, they that commit the ſin unto Death may have theſe,</hi> Heb. 10.26. <hi>There are waſhed Swine,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.20, &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Theſe Parents are <hi>Confederate viſible Believers,</hi> as hath been proved. They are in Covenant with God, He is <hi>their God,</hi> God accepteth them as <hi>His People, His Children;</hi> the Lord hath ſealed to them the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Faith,</hi> Baptized them <hi>into Chriſt,</hi> and they <hi>Own this God, Submit to his Rules,</hi> &amp;c. and therefore in Eccleſiaſtical account they are viſible Believers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is a very palpable Fallacy in citing theſe Scriptures to prove the contrary. <hi>The vileſt perſons</hi> (ſay they) <hi>may have theſe:</hi> Indeed the Scriptures prove that ſome vile perſons may have ſome <hi>one</hi> of theſe; as <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. proveth, that wicked men may have <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> but theſe have <hi>knowledge,</hi> and alſo <hi>Not ſcandalous in life,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo may be ſaid of the reſt. But which of theſe, or any other, doth prove, That ſuch perſons as have all theſe Qualifications con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctly, are <hi>vile perſons,</hi> or not viſible Believers in Eccleſiaſtical ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, or in Scripture account, and not true Members of the viſible Church? It is true, that ſuch as theſe may <hi>fall away,</hi> and become <hi>vile,</hi> Heb. 10 26. but may not ſuch as come into the Church by the faireſt Profeſſion of Faith, prove ſo <hi>vile</hi> alſo? and were they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no <hi>viſible Believers</hi> before ſuch a fall?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Theſe very Scriptures, or moſt of them here alledged, ſpeak of ſuch perſons (though ſo <hi>vile,</hi> as is ſaid) who being adult chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Church, did yet continue Members of the viſible Church, and they and their ſeed partake of Priviledges; and therefore ſuch Scriptures cannot reach this caſe, to diſprove the Memberſhip of theſe in the viſible Church, becauſe they are not viſible Believers, theſe being farre better Members then thoſe were: and I wonder that our Brethren do not obſerve it; or if they do, why ſhould they alledge ſuch Scriptures in this caſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Object. <hi>But their giving up of themſelves and their children to God, implies Faith,</hi> 2 Cor. 8.5.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Our Brethren grant, <hi>that it may imply Faith, but in perſons
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:191784:29"/>no better qualified it cannot imply it. There is a giving up of the Firſt-born of man and beaſt to God,</hi> Exod. 13.2, 12. &amp; 22.29.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> To ſay, <hi>That in ſuch perſons no better qualified it cannot im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Faith,</hi> and that without any Reaſon rendred, is againſt the Rule of <hi>Love,</hi> that <hi>hopeth all things</hi> to be hoped, as this is confeſſed to be, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>it may imply i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> No doubt, a perſon thus qualified in <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Converſation,</hi> may give up himſelf to God in ſuch a manner, that the moſt diſcerning Church would receive him as a true viſible Believer into full Communion regularly. The Eunuch's Confeſſion, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God,</hi> was juſtly taken for true Faith. To ſay, <hi>There is a giving up of the Firſt-born of man and beaſt to God</hi> (if it be not a Scoff) it argueth a very ſlight thought of ſo ſolemn a Profeſſion before God and his People: for what Compariſon is there between theſe two?</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 3. <q>
                     <hi>Where there is no Foederal Holineſs, there is no right to Baptiſm. But where neither Parent is a Believer, there is no Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-holineſs,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. <hi>where not onely one of the Parents muſt be in Covenant, but a Believer, that the children be foederally holy. Neither is it rightly Objected, That a Believer is oppoſed there to an Infidel: for the children were not upon their ceaſing to be Infidels, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: So that themſelves were Believers, or their children foederally holy; They were</hi> Catechumeni, <hi>and</hi> Competentes, <hi>before</hi> Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deles.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Did the Primitive Churches receive any that were not viſible Believers into the Churches? Surely in the Apoſtles account <hi>The Church of God,</hi> and <hi>Sanctified in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> is all one, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. So the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> are called <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 1 1. Col. 1 2. Why th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n is it ſaid, that <hi>the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents muſt be not onely in Church-covenant, but alſo Believers?</hi> as if the one did not neceſſarily ſuppoſe and infer the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it is rightly ſaid, <hi>That in ceaſing to be Infidels they were Believers in Eccleſiaſtical account,</hi> is evident, in that Infidels and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers are the ſame in Scripture-phraſe, and both oppoſed to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15. <hi>Be not unequally yoked with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> that is, with Infidels, as appeareth <hi>ver.</hi> 15. <hi>What part hath a Believer with an Infidel?</hi> Now I appeal to our Brethren, whether this Rule
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:191784:30"/>of the Apoſtle would allow the Parents in queſtion deſcribed in the fifth Propoſition, to Marry with an Heathen, Indian, or like Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del; if not, then in the Scripture account he is a Believer, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he ſhould not be <hi>unequally yoked</hi> with ſuch an one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As for that Diſtinction of <hi>Catechumeni, Competentes,</hi> and <hi>Fideles,</hi> the Scripture knoweth no ſuch thing; for, <hi>Lydia and her houſe were Baptized together,</hi> Acts 16.15. and the Jaylor and his houſe <hi>ſtraightway.</hi> That diſtinction came into the Church after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and was applied to new Converts, as well as to the Church-ſeed.</p>
               <p>But our Brethren adde further, <q>
                     <hi>That elſe, or otherwiſe were your children unclean, cannot be meant onely of Infidels; for ſo we may make mad work of Scripture: as</hi> Deut. 4.29. <hi>Jehovah is God, and none elſe; if any ſhould ſay, There may be another God to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, it would be a ſad Exception: So</hi> Rev. 2.15. <hi>Repent, or I will come againſt thee; ſhall another Church ſay, It will not be ſo with us?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean,</hi> is meant the uncleanneſs of Infidels, is clear by the Rule of Contraries. For, if <hi>to be holy,</hi> be meant of <hi>the holineſs of the Covenant;</hi> then <hi>to be unclean,</hi> is the uncleanneſs of ſuch as are <hi>ſtrangers from the Covenant,</hi> and ſo <hi>without God in the world,</hi> that is, Infidels, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. And what are the children of ſuch as have both Parents <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> but Infidels in the Apoſtles ſenſe? But for that inference, That by like reaſon might be inferred from that propoſition, <hi>There is no God elſe,</hi> that <hi>There may be another God to the Gentiles;</hi> I confeſs my ſhallow underſtanding cannot ſee any Compariſon between thoſe two propoſitions, but onely that the word <hi>Elſe</hi> is in them both; the one being a disjunct Axiome, <hi>Your children are clean,</hi> or <hi>elſe unclean,</hi> and the other a ſimple Axiome, where the word <hi>Elſe</hi> is of another uſe and ſenſe then in the former. But be it ſo, that it is ſo <hi>ſad an Exception</hi> from a general propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Jehovah is God, and none elſe,</hi> to ſay, <hi>Yet there may be another God to the Gentiles;</hi> or to ſay, The threatnings of Chriſt to the Churches <hi>yet belong not to us:</hi> Our Brethren may then conſider, when the Apoſtle ſaith of Church-members, <hi>Your children are holy,</hi> to make ſuch an Exception, and ſay, <hi>Not ſo, but onely the children
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:191784:30"/>of Members in full Communion are holy,</hi> whether this be not a ſad Exception alſo.</p>
               <p>Reaſ 4. <q>
                     <hi>The being in Covenant doth not priviledge to Baptiſm, without viſible Repentance in Parents,</hi> Acts. 2.38, 39. <hi>The Jews were in Covenant, and pricked to the heart, yet they were openly called to Repent: So</hi> John Baptiſt <hi>thought,</hi> Mat. 3.8, 9.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The Jews being in Covenant did priviledge their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the Benefits of that Covenant they were in, <hi>viz.</hi> Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Sacrifices, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. But there was great reaſon they ſhould be called to Repentance, when they were to enter into the Goſpel-diſpenſation of the Covenant, becauſe the Church of the Jews was grown ſo corrupt; and thoſe in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. being guilty of the Blood of the Son of God: and hence <hi>John</hi> was ſent to prepare a people for the Lord by the Doctrine of Repentance. But when <hi>Philip</hi> had to do with the Eunuch, a godly Proſelyte, he onely called him to Faith in the Perſon of Chriſt as the Son of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though Faith and Repentance, in a viſible Profeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, be required at the firſt admiſſion into the Church; yet theſe are not required in the ſame manner in perſons regularly admitted, to priviledge their ſeed to Baptiſm. What Rule or Example requireth a Church-member to make Profeſſion of viſible Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo oft as he hath a childe to be Baptized? Or in caſe a Church-member declineth, and giveth cauſe of much doubt of the ſoundneſs of his Faith and Repentance; What Rule will debarre his childe from Baptiſm, ſo long as he continueth a Member of the Church? Now our queſtion is of <hi>Perſons regularly admitted, and continuing in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reaſ. 5. <q>
                     <hi>The Covenant is limited to ſuch as obey God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Priviledges of the Covenant,</hi> Deut. 7.9. Neh. 1.5. Dan. 9.5.</q> 
                  <hi>He keepeth Covenant and Mercy to them that love him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is a frequent Miſtake, to apply that which is ſpoken of <hi>the ſaving Benefits of the Covenant,</hi> to <hi>the Outward Priviledges thereof;</hi> the firſt God performs to ſuch as love and obey him ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, yet the other he continueth to all ſuch as do not fall away from the Outward Profeſſion of the Covenant. Take theſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:191784:31"/>named: Did not Church-priviledges belong to all Iſrael, when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake that word, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9. that <hi>God keepeth Mercy and Covenant to them that love him?</hi> and yet he giveth a ſad teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.24. <hi>You have been rebellious againſt the Lord ever ſince I knew you.</hi> So in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time, did not all that were of the <hi>holy ſeed</hi> enjoy Church-priviledges, when <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke that word, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.5? and yet the ſtory ſpeaketh of many evils amongſt them, that ſhew they were Scandalous in life, which theſe are not, and have many other good Qualifications beſides that alſo.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 6. <q>
                     <hi>From the tenour and manner of the Covenant made with</hi> Abraham, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.8. <hi>when God ſaw his heart faithful before him. So</hi> Gen. 17.1, 7. <hi>Walk before me, and be upright, and I will be a God to thee and thy ſeed,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is the ſame Reaſon with the former, built upon the ſame Miſtake, and may have the ſame Anſwer. I readily grant, That all that Enter into Covenant with God ought to <hi>Love him, Obey him, Walk uprightly before him:</hi> and what is ſaid <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7, 9. that <hi>They that are of the Faith, are bleſſed with faithful Abraham:</hi> Faith and Holineſs is the duty of every Church-member, for want whereof he falleth ſhort of all the Saving Bleſſings of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. But doth it follow, that ſuch as are in Church-covenant, and do not perform th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe Duties, are thereby deprived of the Outward Priviledges and the Means of Grace, and that before they be regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt out of the Church? Were there not many corrupt Members in the Church, not onely of Iſrael, but alſo in Goſpel-Churches, as of <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> the <hi>Churches of Aſia,</hi> Rev. 2. &amp; 3. who did enjoy Church-priviledges, till they were caſt ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or till God actually <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved their Candleſticks?</hi> It was indeed a ſin reproved to <hi>ſuffer ſuch,</hi> but ſo long as they were ſuffered, they regularly enjoyed the Outward Priviledges.</p>
               <p>Here our Brethren endeavour to Anſwer two Objections.</p>
               <p>Obj 1. <q>
                     <hi>The Covenant-Bleſſing was conveyed with Circumciſion ſucceſſively to the following generations.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. <q>
                     <hi>We muſt conſider, that</hi> Gal. 3.14. <hi>that is expreſſed to be the Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>that ſhould come upon the Gentiles, not the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of</hi> Jacob (<hi>as Mr.</hi> Cotton <hi>hath judic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ouſly noted upon the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:191784:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>place.</hi>) <hi>Now</hi> Abrahams <hi>Covenant, and the Bleſſing thereof, is confirmed onely to thoſe that walk uprightly with God, as</hi> Abraham <hi>did.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> That difference Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> put between the Bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> may hold in this, That God continued all the Sons of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and their Poſterity, in the Covenant; not ſo of <hi>Abraham: Iſhmael</hi> and his ſeed, and the Sons of <hi>Keturah,</hi> were not ſo; and ſo <hi>Eſau</hi> and his ſeed, being the Poſterity of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. And that ſeemeth to be the meaning of that ſpeech of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 49.26. that <hi>His bleſſing prevailed above the bleſſing of his Progenitors.</hi> But this difference cannot hold in reſpect of the tenour of the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> for <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l,</hi> though graceleſs, was taken into <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in it, till for his ſin he was caſt out. So <hi>Eſau</hi> in Covenant, till for his <hi>Profaneneſs he was rejected,</hi> Heb. 12. Was not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Covenant to the ſeed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> the performance of Gods <hi>Everlaſting Covenant</hi> made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> to <hi>be a God to his ſeed af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er him in their generations?</hi> as is evident, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.15. &amp; 6.3, 4. Was there ever any Covenant made with <hi>Jacob</hi> and his ſeed, upon any other terms then the Covenant of <hi>Abraham?</hi> Did not the Lord require Faith and Holineſs of the Poſterity of <hi>Jacob,</hi> as he did of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham?</hi> and therefore this is nothing to hinder the continual ſucceſſion of the <hi>Covenant of Abraham in the Gentile Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj. 2. <q>
                     <hi>It will be ſaid, God promiſed that he would be a God to him and his ſeed in their generations, for an everlaſting Covenant.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. <q>
                     <hi>Is it that all the carnall ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>in all ſucceeding generations, ſhould have God to be their God? Then the Jews are not yet broken off; contrary to</hi> Rom. 11. <hi>This ſeed is</hi> 1. <hi>Onely ſuch of the carnall ſeed with whom the Covenant was eſtabliſhed, by walking in the ſteps of</hi> Abrahams <hi>Faith.</hi> 2. <hi>His ſpirituall ſeed, who are onely meant in that Everlaſting covenant.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. It is granted, that the Outward Diſpenſation of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is not <hi>Abſolute,</hi> but <hi>Conditionall,</hi> in reſpect of the ſucceſſion thereof: The Lord is ever mindful of his Covenant, and that ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly; till his People break his Covenant, he never caſts them out. But there are many tranſgreſſions againſt the Covenant, that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:191784:32"/>do not break off a People from the viſible Covenant, and the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof: and therefore ſo long as the Lord doth not caſt them out of the viſible Church (wherein his patience is very long) the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges thereof continue to their ſucceeding generations everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, even to ſuch as are here called <hi>the Carnall ſeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It doth not ſavour well, that our Brethren ſo frequently call the Church-ſeed <hi>A Carnall ſeed:</hi> We know whoſe Phraſe it is, and to what it tendeth, even <hi>To deny Baptiſm to them.</hi> The Scripture calls them <hi>The holy Seed, An holy Nation, Royall Prieſthood,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Your children are holy,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. God never enters into covenant with any as a <hi>Carnall ſeed,</hi> but as <hi>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>holy People to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. What difference is there between the <hi>Carnall ſeed</hi> walking in the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his <hi>Spirituall ſeed?</hi> If the <hi>Everlaſting Covenant</hi> belong onely to ſuch, then the Priviledges of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant belong not to any Church-member, till he come up to <hi>Walk in the Faith of Abraham,</hi> which is the Tenent of (we know whom.)</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 7. <q>
                     <hi>It is irregular to receive perſons with no better Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations into Covenant; we mean, Ignorant, unbelieving, and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent perſons, into Publick and Perſonal Covenant. Church-covena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters muſt be viſible Saints,</hi> Pſal. 50.5, 16. <hi>Faith, Repentance and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience are required to Covenant with God. It is a palpable untruth for an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliever to engage himſelf to keep the Lords Covenant, whereof Faith is the condition,</hi> Joh. 3.16.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is a great Miſtake, to think theſe in queſtion are to be received into the Covenant, when they come to own their Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſmal Covenant publickly. Our Brethren confeſs <hi>they are in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> Acts 2. which is Sealed up to themby Baptiſm, and that in their own perſons, as was before proved from <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.10, 11, 12. This Publick <hi>Owning of the Covenant,</hi> is but the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of their continuance in it, or a renewing of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To cenſure theſe for <hi>Ignorant perſons,</hi> that underſtand the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Faith (which contains all the Grounds of Religion, as is before proved) and for <hi>Impenitent ſinners, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> whom <hi>God hath received,</hi> owned as <hi>His children,</hi> and <hi>Believers,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14, 15. who live <hi>without Scandall</hi> (which implieth regular Satisfaction for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:191784:32"/>offences) who <hi>give up themſelves to God, Submit to his Government;</hi> to lay all this upon them without Proof, is farre from the Rule of Charity. Surely, they are better Saints then thoſe mentioned by our Brethren <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50.5, 16. Neither do theſe viſibly <hi>hate inſtruction,</hi> in the ſenſe there ſpoken of, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. for they are charged to <hi>conſent with Thieves,</hi> to <hi>partake with Adulterers,</hi> to <hi>give their mouthes to evill,</hi> &amp;c. which cannot be ſaid of theſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What though <hi>Faith, Repentance and Obedience,</hi> and that in truth, <hi>be required of all Covenanters with God;</hi> doth it follow, that ſuch as being in Church-covenant want theſe things, or do not ſo clearly and ſully hold forth theſe by a viſible Profeſſion, that all ſuch have no right to the outward Priviledges? This indeed is the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their Reaſoning all along; but the inconſequence thereof who doth not ſee, that is acquainted with the Scripture ſtory?</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 8. <q>
                     <hi>That Practice that expoſeth the Blood of Chriſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Baptiſm to profanation, the Church to pollution,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is not to be admitted. But the Baptizing of the children of ſuch as are not viſible Believers doth all this. Therefore it is not to be admitted.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. I might grant the Argument: It doth not conclude againſt theſe whom <hi>God hath received</hi> as <hi>holy,</hi> as viſible <hi>Believers, Baptized into Chriſt,</hi> as hath been oft proved from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. with <hi>chap.</hi> 7.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By this Reaſon, when Members received by Profeſſion of Faith and Repentance in adult age, do decline, and appear to have as little Faith as theſe are ſuppoſed to have, though under no cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſuch muſt not have their childrne Baptized; or elſe all thoſe conſequences will follow. This may ſuffice to Anſwer the Reaſon itſelf. The Proofs I ſhall touch afterward.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 9. <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe theſe adult children, if they were not Baptized themſelves, might not be Baptized in this eſtate, and therefore cannot intitle their ſeed unto it. A man muſt ſtand poſſeſſed of a right, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can make it over to another. Acts</hi> a non habente poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, <hi>are void in Law.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is a ſtrange kinde of Reaſoning: By ſuppoſing that a man hath not that thing which indeed he hath, and therefore he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not convey that which he hath. Let me take away a man's Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:191784:33"/>and Poſſeſſion of his Lands, and it is true he cannot make a good Conveyance; but may he not then convey what he hath Evidences and Poſſeſſion of? There are ſome Members in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, who ſuppoſe they were not admitted, would not now be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; doth it therefore follow, that their children may not be Baptized? If acts of ſuch as have no right and power themſelves, are void; then acts of ſuch as have a right and power, are valid: Now theſe are Church-members, and Baptized, and therefore their conveyance of Baptiſm is valid, by this Argument. And yet it would be hard for our Brethren to prove, that theſe being Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members ſo qualified, might not be Baptized, if they had not been Baptized.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 10. <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe there is but one way of Entrance into the Church for all ſorts of perſons, which way is not here mentioned, and this way is Chriſt,</hi> Joh. 10.7. <hi>But this Propoſition holdeth forth no perſonall Entrance by Chriſt: if they be gotten</hi> in <hi>ſome other way, they are Thieves and Robbers. The danger is ſeen in him that had not on the Wedding-garment, the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt: which being ſo pernicious, how can the Church be blameleſs in bringing them</hi> in <hi>this way?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Let the interpretation of <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. be granted at preſent; I Anſwer, That theſe children came into the Church <hi>by Chriſt,</hi> for they came in by the Goſpel-Covenant, as our Brethren grant from <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. And is not <hi>Chriſt the Mediator of that Covenant?</hi> Yea are they not <hi>Baptized into Chriſt?</hi> Are not the Blood and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Chriſt <hi>Scaled up to them in Baptiſm?</hi> But our Brethren ſeem wholly to forget that, or to make a Nothing of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When this Covenant (which is called <hi>The covenant of God in Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.17.) is <hi>Solemnly owned by them, wherein they give up themſelves to God, and ſubmit to the Government of Chriſt in the Church;</hi> Is there nothing of Chriſt in all this?</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The danger of wanting the Wedding-garment,</hi> is as great to ſuch as come in with the faireſt Profeſſion of Faith, as to theſe; and is the Church blameable for admitting ſuch, becauſe their <hi>danger is ſo great,</hi> when ſuch want the <hi>Wedding-garment?</hi> But ſeeing our Brethren urge ſo much <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. let them conſider <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>The
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:191784:33"/>hireling careth not for the ſheep.</hi> We have more cauſe to fear how we ſhall anſwer for our careleſs Neglect of theſe <hi>Lambs of Chriſt,</hi> then for our Receiving them into the <hi>Fold of Chriſt,</hi> for which we have our Warrant from Chriſt. And withall, let us remember that weighty Charge <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.15, 16. <hi>Looking diligently, leſt any fail of the grace of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>leſt there be a profane perſon, as</hi> Eſau, <hi>who for a morſell of meat ſold his Birthright.</hi> It ſeemeth the Apoſtle did think there was a <hi>Precious Birthright,</hi> and that it was the duty of the Church to look diligently to the preſervation and improvement of it. Let us then take heed we do not take it from them, before the Rule of Chriſt doth require it.</p>
               <p>By this whole Diſcourſe, and by theſe <hi>Ten Reaſons,</hi> we may now fully ſee upon what Principles our Brethren ground their <hi>Anti-Synodalia,</hi> or their <hi>Poſitions</hi> wherein they Diſſent from the Synod. And therefore, ſeeing the Prefacer complains that <hi>Their Tenent is laden with Reproaches of Anabaptiſm,</hi> I ſhall crave leave (before I paſs on) to preſent unto their ſerious Conſideration, what Advantages they put into the hands of the Anabaptiſts, who, I fear, will make ſuch uſe hereof as our Brethren would not willingly allow them to do. It is true, that our Brethren confeſs with us, <hi>That the Covenant of God with</hi> Abraham <hi>and his ſeed, is the Goſpel-covenant, and doth belong to the Faithfull and their ſeed,</hi> Acts 2.38, 39. But do they not with their <hi>Diſtinctions,</hi> in effect, take away what they have given them? <hi>They are Members in generall</hi> (ſay they) but come to the particular, and it is onely <hi>as wrapped up in their Parents Covenant;</hi> they are not <hi>actual</hi> or <hi>perſonal Members.</hi> And that Memberſhip in their Parents, and their Foederal Holineſs, reacheth no further then <hi>their Minority,</hi> pag. 37. And what Church-Ordinances are they capable of in that time, eſpecially if that were true which ſome ſuggeſt, That <hi>Iſhmael came into the Church by Profeſſion of Faith as an adult Member at thirteen years of age?</hi> And, if at <hi>adult age</hi> they come not up by Profeſſion of Faith and Grace, to Enter into perſonal Covenant, and ſo to a new Memberſhip, <hi>hey have no right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Church-priviledges.</hi> And may not a Convert out of Paganiſm, upon ſuch terms, enjoy as much as this? And as for <hi>Church-watch and Government,</hi> it cannot <hi>reach them, but by their Parents,</hi> as it may reach an Infidel-ſervant: and when their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:191784:34"/>Parents be dead, and they left to the care of ſuch as are not of the Church, how ſhall it then touch them at all? And when their <hi>Owning of the Covenant</hi> is accounted <hi>the Form of their Memberſhip;</hi> what is this, but to make a Nullity of their Covenant ſealed in Baptiſm? So that it will, I fear, ſeem to the Anabaptiſts, <hi>That to Baptize Infants, is to ſet a Seal to a Blank, or to a Covenant of no uſe to them.</hi> Again, when our Brethren ſo oft deny the viſible Covenant, and the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof, to ſuch as want the inward Grace; and affirm, <hi>That the Covenant, and the Priviledges thereof, are limited to thoſe that with</hi> Abraham <hi>walk with God, whoſe heart was faithfull; who love God, and keep his commandments,</hi> pag. 29. Will not the Anabaptiſts be ready to inferre, <hi>Therefore Infants wanting that Grace,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>have no right to the Covenant, or to Baptiſm the Priviledge of it?</hi> Again, when our Brethren ſo oft confound the Outward and Inward Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant, alledging the <hi>Scandalous ſins of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members in the Scripture,</hi> to prove that theſe in queſtion are <hi>Self-Excommunicated,</hi> and have no intereſt in the Outward Covenant, or Priviledges thereof; Is not this a Miſtake which they will make advantage of? Laſtly, when they ſay, That the Practice of the fifth Propoſition <hi>expoſeth the Blood of Chriſt to contempt, Baptiſm to be profaned, bringeth pollution into the Church,</hi> &amp;c. what are the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? <hi>For</hi> (ſay they) <hi>it imparteth the Blood of the Covenant to thoſe that are not viſible Believers, ſets the Seal to a Blank, ſevereth Baptiſm from the ſtipulation of a good conſcience, bringeth the uncircumciſed in heart into the Sanctuary.</hi> But they oft confeſs, that <hi>Infants have no Faith, They are a carnall ſeed,</hi> &amp;c. And is it not a juſt fear, that the Anabaptiſts will be ready to inferre, <hi>Therefore to baptize Infants, is to expoſe the Blood of Chriſt to contempt,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
               <p>I know our Brethren will ſay, <hi>We do not require Faith and Grace in the Infants, but in the Parents onely:</hi> But yet when generally we ground the Baptiſm of Infants upon the Covenant of God to the Parents and their ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. and prove they are <hi>Diſciples, Members of the viſible Church,</hi> and therefore to be Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized; I wiſh our Brethren may conſider, how greatly this ground is weakned by Denial of Gods Covenant to <hi>their Perſons,</hi> and onely as <hi>in their Parents;</hi> and by making it ſo ſlight a matter, as to <hi>wear out</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:191784:34"/>with their Minority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And alſo let them conſider, how ſuitable their Notions and Principles before-named, are to the Arguments and Grounds of Denial of Baptiſm to all Infants, as is eaſie to ſee in all the Books of Antipoedobaptiſts. Theſe things I mention, that our Brethren may keep further off from this danger, which themſelves count <hi>a Reproach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall now proceed to conſider the Anſwers of our Brethren to the Arguments of the Synod for the proof of the fifth Propoſition.</p>
               <q>Arg. 1. <hi>Theſe children are partakers of the main ground of baptizing any children whatſoever, and neither the parents nor the children do put in any barre to hinder it. This ground is the Intereſt in the Covenant,</hi> Gen. 17.7, 9, 10, 11. Acts 2.39. Col. 2.10, 11.</q>
               <p>"<hi>Anſ.</hi> They anſwer in general, that <hi>Faith is the main ground of Baptiſm,</hi> Rom. 4.11. Acts 8.37 &amp; 19.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. Here is no anſwer to the Scriptures alledged, which are very full: <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10, 11. <hi>This is my Covenant which ye ſhall keep, Every Male-childe ſhall be circumciſed: It ſhall be a token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant between me and you.</hi> So <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38, 39. <hi>The Promiſe is to you and your children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Faith is the Condition of the Covenant; yet the outward Seal had reference to the outward Covenant it ſelf: for <hi>Lo,</hi> and other Believers, could not partake of Circumciſion, but by entring into that viſible Covenant with <hi>Abraham.</hi> And our Brethren after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward do grant, That <hi>the Church-covenant is the next ground of the dispenſation of the Seals:</hi> Now they that have the <hi>next ground,</hi> are ſuppoſed to have the more remote.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 2. <hi>More particularly,</hi> they ſay, <hi>the Covenant is not the main ground of Baptiſm. For,</hi> 1. <hi>though they had</hi> Abraham <hi>for their father, yet</hi> John<hi>'s Baptiſm takes away that Plea,</hi> Mat. 3.8, 9. <hi>and calls for Repentance.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply. John</hi> took away their vain confidence in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for Righteouſneſs and Life, as the Prophets alſo frequently did, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 58. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. <hi>Mic.</hi> 6. But he took not away the outward Priviledges of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, as Circumciſion, Sacrifices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>John</hi> indeed calls for Repentance in a people ſo corrupt, to fit them for a more Goſpel-diſpenſation, to make them <hi>a People pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:191784:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>for the Lord.</hi> But that is not the caſe of theſe in the fifth Propoſition, who are in the Goſpel covenant, and have the Seal of Baptiſm.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <q>2. <hi>We muſt diſtinguiſh</hi> (ſay they) <hi>between the Covenant of Grace, and the Church-covenant, which differ very much: for the Covenant of Grace belongeth onely to the Elect, and true Believers, which the Church cannot infallibly judge who they are. But the Church-covenant (which is the next ground of the diſpenſation of the Seal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>) requireth mutuall conſent of them that are admitted into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, to walk with God according to the Gospel. The Covenant of Grace is made to the children in the Parents, but is eſtabliſhed onely by the reſtipulation of Faith and Repentance,</hi> Gen. 17.7, 9. Rom. 11.20. <hi>Thou ſtandeſt by Faith.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. I cannot ſee how theſe things can conſiſt one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. For, if the Covenant of Grace belongeth onely <hi>to the Elect and true Believers;</hi> and this Covenant of Grace be <hi>made with the childe in the Parents:</hi> then the childe and Parents muſt be <hi>Elect, and true Believers;</hi> which will not be granted. Again, if the difference of the Church-covenant ſtands in this, That it <hi>requrreth mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to walk with God;</hi> how ſhall Infants partake of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covenant and Baptiſm, whereof it is the next ground.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Diſtinction, as here laid down, doth not prove the thing it was brought for, but rather yield the ſame: For, 1. It is yielded that <hi>the Church-covenant is the next ground of Baptiſm;</hi> and that which is the next ground and immediate, is the chief for it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the remote; and the remote grounds, without the next, could not give right to Baptiſm, and therefore this is the chief ground. Beſides, when it is ſaid, that <hi>the Covenant of Grace is made to the childe in the Parents,</hi> then ſtill the Covenant, even of Grace alſo, is the ground of Baptiſm. <hi>But</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the eſtabliſhment is upon the reſtipulation of Faith: Thou ſtandeſt by Faith,</hi> Rom. 11.20. Be it ſo, in reſpect of the Covenant of Grace, and the ſaving Benefits thereof; yet the viſible Covenant, and Diſpenſation of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and Means of Grace, remains to ſuch in the Covenant as do continue in the viſible Profeſſion thereof, as hath been oft proved. That Faith by which the Gentile-Churches ſtand, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:191784:35"/>ſuch a Faith as is oppoſed to that Unbelief for which the Jews were broken off: but they were not broken off for want of holding forth poſitive Saving Faith to the judgement of Charity, but for poſitive Unbelief, whereby they obſtinately rejected Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.21. <hi>They were a diſobedient and gainſaying people.</hi> Acts 13.45. The Apoſtle turned from them to the Gentiles, becauſe they <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted and blaſphemed.</hi> Mat. 21.42, 43. The Kingdome of God was taken from them, becauſe <hi>they rejected Chriſt the Corner ſtone:</hi> See alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 18.5, 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.8, 9. And therefore ſo long as the Gentile Churches do profeſs Jeſus Chriſt, and his Goſpel and Ordinances, they may ſtand in the viſible Covenant, (through the patience of God) though they, or many of their Members, do not hold out ſuch a Profeſſion of Saving Faith viſibly to the judgement of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: otherwiſer we muſt Unchurch many ſuch Societies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians whom the Lord hath not Unchurched, but continueth to them the Means and Ordinances of Grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I deny that there is ſuch a difference between the <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covenant</hi> and that of <hi>Grace:</hi> for, as was ſaid in the ſecond Propoſition premiſed, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. there is indeed a differing diſpenſation of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace in the Church, <hi>viz. Outwardly,</hi> in the Priviledges, Ordinances, and Means of Grace to the whole viſible Church; or <hi>Inwardly,</hi> in the Saving Benefits thereof to true Believers. Now that the Diſpenſation of the Covenant of God to the whole viſible Church, is the Diſpenſation of the Covenant of Grace, is proved: 1. Becauſe God giveth himſelf to be the God of all the viſible Church, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>I will be thy God;</hi> and he avoucheth them to be <hi>His People,</hi> and they avouch him to be <hi>Their God,</hi> Deut. 26.17, 18. Now this is the firſt and chief Benefit of the Covenant of Grace, and containeth all the reſt, as Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> noteth upon that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. 2. Becauſe the Means of Grace and Life, and the offer of Chriſt and Grace, is given to all in the viſible Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.4. 3. Becauſe all in Church-covenant ſtand bound thereby to Believe, Repent, and perform the conditions of the Covenant of Grace: and this our Brethren confeſs, that <hi>Church-covenant requires they ſhould walk with God according to the Goſpel;</hi> which is the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace. I have the more inſiſted on this Paſſage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:191784:36"/>the right underſtanding hereof, is of much uſe to the main Queſtion in debate.</p>
               <q>That theſe in the fifth Propoſition are ſtill in Covenant, <hi>the Synod proveth,</hi> Becauſe they were once in Covenant, and never cut off from it.</q>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this our Brethren Anſwer, <hi>The Lord himſelf diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants them,</hi> Mat. 3. Joh. 8.39, 40, 41, 42. <hi>where the Lord takes away their Plea of the Covenant, and tells them they have the Devil for their Father. And that without any act of Church-diſcipline,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They may reject the counſel of God againſt themſelves, as the Phariſees,</hi> Luke 7. <hi>They may be</hi> Felones de ſe, <hi>as Mr.</hi> Cotton <hi>ſpeaks,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>There are other grounds of breaking off the Covenant, beſides notorious ſins, and incorrigibleneſs therein; as, Not ſtanding by Faith, Not bringing forth f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uit,</hi> Mat. 3.10. <hi>Not doing Righteouſneſs,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.10.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> I have many things to Reply here. 1. Did the Lord himſelf diſcovenant all thoſe out of his viſible Church, ſpoken of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> 8? Were their ſeed thereby cut off from Circu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? Were they excluded from the Sacrifices and Temple-worſhip? Who can believe this? when we ſee the Lord Jeſus ſo oft com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated with them in the Worſhip of God; when he calleth them ſtill <hi>The loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> yea, the <hi>children to whom Bread did belong,</hi> Mat. 15.24, 26. Theſe things were ſpoken of the Jews in general, whereof thoſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. were a part. They were indeed <hi>of the Devil,</hi> not of God, in reſpect of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtate, and ſaving good of the Covenant; yet ſtill in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Covenant, and under the Means of Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If thoſe <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 3. <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 8. had been diſcovenanted of God, doth it follow that theſe in queſtion are ſo? Are theſe <hi>A generation of Vipers, Lyars, Murtherers,</hi> &amp;c that live <hi>without Scandall, Submit to the Government of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c? If the Lawyers and Phariſees <hi>rejected the counſel of God againſt themſelves,</hi> in not being Baptized of <hi>John;</hi> do theſe ſo, that being B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptized themſelves, deſire it alſo for their Seed, and that in ſuch in way, by <hi>Owning Gods Covenant, Giving up themſelves to God, Submitting themſelves to Diſcipline,</hi> &amp;c? If Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> did count ſuch as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> Self-murtherers, doth it follow that theſe are ſuch, that <hi>take hold of the Covenant,</hi> and that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:191784:36"/>in ſome meaſure of truth, for ought is yet proved to the contrary?</p>
               <p n="3">3. I muſt not paſs over this Rigid and Dangerous Principle, without further Examination. The Poſition of our Brethren is, <hi>That God himſelf doth diſcovenant, or caſt out of his viſible Church, ſuch as bring not forth good fruit,</hi> Mat. 3. <hi>that commit ſin, are Lyars,</hi> &amp;c. Joh. 8. <hi>and that without any act of Church-cenſure.</hi> Againſt this I argue:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That theſe were not diſcovenanted of GOd, I proved before. And it doth appear, That the Providence of God continued them under Church-priviledges and Ordinances, at leaſt till Goſpel-Churches were erected, after the Aſcenſion of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If the Lord Jeſus hath ordained and commanded Church-diſcipline for the <hi>ſaving of Offenders,</hi> and the <hi>Purging of his Church,</hi> then he doth not diſcovenant ſuch without Church-cenſures. But ſo it is, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Therefore he doth it not himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. The reaſon of the Conſequence is, Becauſe if God himſelf did diſcovenant them, Church-cenſures were uſeleſs and vain. To what end ſhould the Church cut off one that is already a Non-member? what have they to do with ſuch as are <hi>without?</hi> why ſhould <hi>Corinth</hi> be blamed for <hi>ſuffering that Leaven,</hi> if God himſelf had caſt it out?</p>
               <p n="3">3. This ſuppoſed <hi>Diſcovenanting by God himſelf,</hi> fruſtrates the great and chief End of Church diſcipline, <hi>viz. To heal and ſave the Sinner:</hi> for, the Church having now no power over them, they muſt periſh, being without the Means of their Recovery, except God reſtore them immediately; at leaſt they are deprived of that ſpecial Means appointed and bleſſed of God to that end.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What confuſion would this bring into the Church? For, how ſhall the Church know when God hath diſcovenanted this or that man? whether ſo ſoon as he hath committed ſuch ſins, or how long Gods patience will bear with him? And how ſhall the Church prove againſt any ſuch, That God hath indeed diſcovenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him? Theſe things, and much more that might be ſaid, may put our Brethren to finde ſome other meaning of <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.10. and ſuch like Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Arg. 2. <hi>The children of the Parents in queſtion are either child on
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:191784:37"/>of the Covenant, or ſtrangers from it,</hi> Eph. 2.12. <hi>Holy, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. <hi>within the Church, or without,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.12. <hi>ſuch as have God for their God, or without God in the world,</hi> Eph. 2.12. <hi>But he that conſidereth the terms of the Propoſition, will not affirm the latter; and the former being granted, inferreth their right to Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>The Aſſumption is denied, becauſe the children in queſtion diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covenant themſelves, not keeping the conditions of the Covenant; Not walking with God, Not loving God,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 7.9. <hi>as they that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Covenant of their fathers,</hi> Deut. 29.25. <hi>And what do theſe that come not up to the conditions of it? God may caſt off for ſins of Omiſſion,</hi> 1 Sam. 15. <hi>ſo for not believing in God.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This being the very Hinge whereupon chiefly this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion doth turn, <hi>viz. Whether, and how theſe Church-members are cut off from their Memberſhip in the viſible Church?</hi> I deſire the Reader to obſerve well the Anſwer of our Brethren, and their Reaſons thereof. Sometime they ſay, <hi>God Diſcovenanteth them;</hi> which hath been examined: Sometime, that <hi>They Diſcovenant themſelve;</hi> which alſo hath been ſpoken to before. To this Refuge they now again betake themſelves. Their Reaſon here alledged I ſhall conſider, which ſtandeth thus: <hi>Church-members which do not come up to the conditions of the Covenant,</hi> viz. <hi>To walk with God, Love God, keep his Commandments, Believe in God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>do Diſcovenant themſelves. But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe Church-members deſcribed in the fifth Propoſition, do not walk with God, Love God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore they do Diſcovenant themſelves.</hi> The Propoſition they would prove from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 105.8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.25. To this I anſwer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. By denying the Propoſition. As for the Proofs, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 17.1. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 105. Theſe Scriptures prove it is the duty of ſuch as enter into Covenant with God, to <hi>Walk with God. To be upright, To love God,</hi> &amp;c. and that God performs to ſuch the Saving Benefits of the Covenant: but they do not prove, that ſimply by the neglect of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe duties eſpecially without <hi>Impenitence</hi> added, they do actually D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>covenant themſelves out of the viſible Church and from the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof, and the Means of Grace therein. The groſs neglect of the duties of the Covenant perſiſted in obſtinately and impenitently,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:191784:37"/>may deſerve Cenſures: but that the want of ſuch graces, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Covenant, doth actually cut off ſuch from the viſible Church, is an Aſſertion never heard of in the Book of God, nor I think in any the beſt Reformed Church to this day. Surely <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> did not <hi>Walk with God, Love God, Believe in God,</hi> in our Brethrens ſenſe; yet they continued in the Church, till for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <hi>Profaneneſs</hi> the one was <hi>caſt out</hi> by Gods appointment, and the other <hi>rejected,</hi> Heb. 12.17. When <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, that <hi>The Lord keepeth Covenant and Mercy with them that love him,</hi> &amp;c. were there not multitudes in Iſrael that came not up to theſe duties of the Covenant, in our Brethrens ſenſe, that yet were Gods <hi>Holy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Royall Nation,</hi> enjoying all Church-priviledges? and ſo all along through the ſtory of all the Scriptures. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.25. renders indeed the cauſe of the great Plagues upon Iſrael, to be their <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Covenant:</hi> But what was that <hi>forſaking of the Covenant?</hi> was it their not coming up to theſe terms of it, to <hi>Walk with God, Love God, Believe in God with a viſible ſaving Faith?</hi> Nothing leſs: but becauſe <hi>they went and ſerved other gods, and worſhipped them,</hi> ver. 26. As for the caſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 Sam. 15. whom <hi>the Lord rejected from being King,</hi> for ſo groſs a diſobedience to an expreſs and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Command; yet we reade not that he was caſt out of the viſible Church: Nor <hi>doth</hi> it follow, that becauſe God <hi>may</hi> juſtly cut off a man from the Church for not believing, or <hi>Sins of Omiſſion,</hi> that therefore he doth ſo; or that therefore a Church-member, by <hi>Sins of Omiſſion,</hi> doth actually cut off himſelf from the viſible Church. Surely theſe are worſe then <hi>farre-fetched and uncertain Conſequences from the Old Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Aſſumption of this Argument; They ſay (but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Proof) <hi>That theſe Parents in the fifth Propoſition do not walk with God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>according to the conditions of the Covenant.</hi> I anſwer, Theſe do outwardly and viſibly, at leaſt, ſo <hi>Walk with God, Love Him, and keep His Commandments,</hi> as the Rule of God doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>A keeping of the viſible Covenant:</hi> Theſe <hi>Profeſs the Faith, are not ſcandalous in life, give up themſelves to God, ſubmit to his Rules and government;</hi> and were not ſuch as theſe all along in the Scripture accepted as the People of God in the viſible Covenant? <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:191784:38"/>when the people profeſſed to <hi>Obey Moſes in all things,</hi> God ſaw they wanted an heart <hi>to fear him, and keep his commandments,</hi> yet he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Covenant with them. How oft are the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> that obſerved the Ordinances of Worſhip, ſaid to <hi>do that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, and to walk in his wayes,</hi> though they wanted that upright walking with God, and love of God, which was required? See 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.17. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.3, 34. And, <hi>Not to walk in the wayes of the Lord,</hi> is charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them when <hi>they walked after Baalim, In the wayes of Jeroboam,</hi> and the like. To conclude, I would demand of our Brethren that hold this way of <hi>Self-Excommunication, Whether any Member doth Excommunicate himſelf by any act that is not Excommunicable (or matter of Excommunication) by the Rule of Church-diſcipline?</hi> If ſo, let us have a Rule for it; if not, ſurely theſe in the fifth Propoſition do not Excommunicate themſelves, for no Rule of Chriſt would allow the Church to caſt them out.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 2. <hi>The children in queſtion</hi> (ſay they) <hi>are in a ſtate of Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality at preſent: and ſuch Chriſt accounts to be againſt him,</hi> Mat. 12.30. <hi>They are neither hot nor cold,</hi> Rev. 3.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply. Mat.</hi> 12.30. ſpeaketh not of ſuch as theſe, for theſe are <hi>for Chriſt,</hi> that <hi>Profeſs the Faith of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Submit to his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> That Saying of Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.40. ſuits better with theſe, <hi>He that is not againſt us, is for us.</hi> As for <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. Chriſt calls that Luke-warm Church, <hi>A golden Candleſtick,</hi> holds their <hi>Stars in his Right hand,</hi> offers to <hi>come in,</hi> &amp;c. So that Chriſt is not ſo quick in diſcovenanting luke-warm ones, as our Brethren ſeem to be.</p>
               <q>Arg. 3. <hi>From the evil conſequences of the contrary Opinion: as,</hi> 1. <hi>To deny the Propoſition, would be to ſtraiten the grace of Chriſt in the Goſpel-diſpenſation, and to make the Church in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment times, in a worſe caſe, relating to their children ſucceſſively, then were the Jews of old.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 1. <hi>This doth not ſtraiten the Gospel-dispenſation, ſeeing it is granted to be extended to all Nations, and to both Sexes, which was not of old.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This indeed the Anabaptiſts anſwer, but it doth not reach the caſe. For, ſuch inlargement of the grace of God in Goſpel-times,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:191784:38"/>would argue rather that it ſhould be enlarged in this Point alſo, and not therefore ſtraitned here, becauſe enlarged in other reſpects. Were it Objected to a Father, That he ſtraitned his wonted favours to his children, in putting them out of the Family; and he ſhould anſwer, <hi>Not ſo, for I have taken in many adopted chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> would this anſwer ſatisfie? Or ſhould he ſay, <hi>Not ſo, for though I kept my Family with Pulſe before, I now give them much better fare:</hi> would not any man ſay, So much is the greater wrong to your children, both to put them out of the Family, and deprive them of their ſhare in the better fare allowed to the Family. Juſt ſo is the caſe here.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 2. <hi>This doth no more ſtraiten the grace of the Covenant, then the keeping of Baptized, especially covenanting Parents from the Lords Supper, ſeeing the circumciſed Jews were not debarred from the paſſover.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The circumciſed Jews did not partake of the Paſſover, without ſuitable legal qualifications, <hi>viz.</hi> A ſtate of legal purity and fitneſs to eat it to the Lord, and therefore they were to inſtruct their children in the meaning of that Service, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.25, 26, 27. In like manner we debarre none from the Lords Supper, but for want of Goſpel qualifications.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 3. <hi>Goſpel-times are in many reſpects Times of Reformation,</hi> Heb. 9.10. <hi>and therefore to build ſo much upon the largeneſs of Jewiſh practices, is a great ſin, ſeeing it is a ſtretching of the narrow way that leads to life, to be as wide as the broad way that leads moſt to deſtruction.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. We build not upon Jewiſh practices Ceremonial, wherein that <hi>Reformation</hi> Heb. 9.10 did conſiſt, as is plain in the Text: but upon the Goſpel-covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that in the ſubſtantials of it, <hi>viz. I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed after thee in their generations,</hi> exemplified in the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is a ſtrange ſpeech to ſay, that <hi>This is a ſtretching of the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way of life, to be as broad,</hi> &amp;c. Surely, Gods enlargement of the Covenant to the Poſterity of <hi>Abraham in their generations,</hi> was an act of Gods grace, tending to bring the more to life, by giving to them the means of grace and life, and therefore was not the <hi>broad way to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtruction.</hi> The <hi>ſtraitneſs of the way to life,</hi> doth not ſtand in reſtraining the means of grace to a few; for why then
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:191784:39"/>ſhould the Lord enlarge the Goſpel to <hi>all Nations</hi> now, more then of old?</p>
               <q>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Conſequence, <hi>To deny the Propoſition, is to render the children of the Jews, when they ſhall be converted, in a worſe condition then they were under the Legal-dispenſation, contrary to</hi> Jer. 30.20. Ezek. 37.25, 26.</q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>This is denied, any more then that they ſhould be in a worſe ſtate if they ſhall not have an High-Prieſt and Temple-worſhip, when they ſhall have in Chriſt a thouſand-fold more: So here is like reaſon in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of His abundant grace.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The loſs of Shadows is nothing, ſeeing they ſhall have the Subſtance in Chriſt: but this being an eſſential Branch of Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> which is the Goſpel-covenant, it cannot be taken away without reall loſs; and the more <hi>abundant grace,</hi> the greater is the loſs, as was ſaid before.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ 2. <hi>This doth no more put them into a worſer ſtate, then tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the Covenant now onely to the next ſeed, which before was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to remote Poſterity.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The Covenant was all along tranſmitted by the next Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to their ſeed in the Old Teſtament: For, ſo long as they were not caſt off by the Lord, he accounted every generation to be <hi>His Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> even in their worſt times. So that the tranſmitting of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Church-priviledges, was ſtill by the next Parents; and when the Parents were broken off, their ſeed were broken off alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. So that there is no ſuch difference.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 3. <hi>To the Scriptures,</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that in</hi> Jer. 30. <hi>ſpeaketh of their return from</hi> Babylon: Ezek. 37. <hi>speaketh of their Calling, when they ſhall be all righteous, and nothing ſhall hinder the continuance of the Covenant,</hi> Iſa. 60.21. Joel 3.17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> If <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. hath any reference to their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet it appeareth to look further, even to the latter times. For <hi>Ver.</hi> 9. it ſpeaketh of <hi>David their King, whom God will raiſe up to them;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 24. of <hi>the latter dayes:</hi> and <hi>Chap.</hi> 31.1. <hi>At the ſame time I will be the God of all the families of Iſrael.</hi> As for thoſe places, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21. <hi>Joel</hi> 3. that ſay, <hi>They ſhall be all righteous, no ſtranger ſhall paſs through them;</hi> ſo that <hi>nothing ſhall hinder the continuance of the Covenant:</hi> The
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:191784:39"/>Covenant then ſhall be continued, according to the Promiſe of God, to <hi>Abrahams ſeed in their generations,</hi> which is enough to the ſcope of this Argument. Beſides, this <hi>continuance of the Covenant</hi> ſhall be by <hi>viſible Faith and Righteouſneſs,</hi> not alwayes by <hi>reall Faith;</hi> for to think there ſhall be no Sin, no Hypocrites then, is groundleſs. <hi>There is none righteous that ſinneth not,</hi> is the general ſtate of all men in this world, till we come to Heaven. And it is evident <hi>Ezek</hi> 37.25. <hi>Zech.</hi> 10.7, 9. that their ſeed are part of that righteous Nation.</p>
               <q>3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Conſequence. <hi>The deniall of the Propoſition, denieth the initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Seal to ſuch as are regularly in the Church and Covenant, to whom the Moſaicall diſpenſation, nay the firſt Inſtitution in the Covenant of</hi> Abraham, <hi>appointed it to be applied,</hi> Gen. 17.9, 10. Joh. 7.22, 23.</q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>This is a begging of the Queſtion: The children in queſtion do not ſtand regularly under the Church-covenant; the contrary is plain</hi> Jer. 9.26. Rom. 2.28. Ezek. 34.7, 9.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> The Queſtion is not begged, but the ground of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is proved, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9, 10. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.22, 23. to which no anſwer is returned.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Seeing theſe Scriptures <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44. and ſuch like, are ſo oft alledged, and here with ſo much confidence in the preſent caſe, I ſhall Examine them more diſtinctly.</p>
               <p>The Queſtion is, <hi>Whether children received into the Church, and Baptized in Infancy, and being grown up, do underſtand the Doctrine of Faith, publickly Profeſs their Aſſent thereto, are not ſcandalous in life, ſolemnly own the Covenant before the Church, wherein they give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to God, and ſubmit to the government of Chriſt in the Church; Whether</hi> (I ſay) <hi>ſuch do not ſtand regularly in the Church:</hi> and, <hi>Whether the Scriptures named do plainly prove the contrary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for the firſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.26. where the Lord threatneth to <hi>puniſh</hi> the circumciſed with the uncircumciſed; for, <hi>all the houſe of Iſrael are uncircumciſed in heart.</hi> To this I anſwer, 1. That this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not <hi>Diſcovenanting them,</hi> but <hi>the Sword.</hi> 2. But ſuppoſe <hi>Diſcovenanting</hi> be included in the other; what were the cauſes thereof, by which they were proved to be <hi>uncircumciſed in heart,</hi> and therefore ſo to be puniſhed? They were all <hi>Adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erers,</hi> ver. 2. <hi>Lyars,</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:191784:40"/>ver. 3. <hi>Slanderers,</hi> ver. 4. <hi>Deceivers,</hi> ver. 5. yea, they <hi>walked after Baal,</hi> ver. 14. And how then doth this place plainly prove, that the perſons deſcribed in the Propoſition <hi>ſtand not regularly in the Church?</hi> As for <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28. ſo oft alledged, however it may have ſome reference to the Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> before ſpoken to, yet it ſeems the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular occaſion and ſcope of that diſcourſe of the <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> is to prove, that God diſtributeth rewards and puniſhments <hi>without reſpect of perſons,</hi> ver. 9, 10, 11 and to take off the Iews confidence in Legal-priviledges in that reſpect, <hi>ver.</hi> 13, 17, 18, 19, 20. but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it cannot be ſpoken with any reference to Church-member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Now in reſpect of Gods diſtribution of rewards and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Circumciſion profited if they kept the Law,</hi> elſe not; and in this reſpect, <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion that kept the Law, was counted Circumciſion:</hi> and ſo in this reſpect, <hi>He is not a Jew that is one outwardly.</hi> &amp;c. But to infer, that every lew that was ſo <hi>outwardly</hi> onely, wanting the <hi>inward circumciſion of the heart,</hi> was there by diſcovenanted out of the viſible Church, this were a ſtrange Doctrine to Scripture-ears. To clear this further: 1. In what reſpect <hi>the circumciſion is made uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, by breaking the Law;</hi> in the ſame reſpect <hi>the uncircumciſion is counted for circumciſion, in them that kept the Law:</hi> but this was never ſo accounted in reſpect of Church-memberſhip and Priviledges; witneſs the caſe of the Centurion <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and his <hi>devout Souldiers,</hi> and others, and therefore not ſo in the former. 2. He ſpeaketh of the <hi>inward circumciſion,</hi> as <hi>having its praiſe of God, not of men:</hi> but we know the outward Circumciſion is approved of the Church, though without the inward, in reſpect of Church-ſtanding and Priviledges, and that according to Gods Rules. 3. The Apoſtle fully cleareth his meaning, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. affirming, <hi>That the advantage of the Jew, and profit of circumciſion, was much every way,</hi> and that <hi>in the committing the Oracles of God to them,</hi> which was a Church-priviledge.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Concerning this place, let it be noted what were the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of <hi>uncircumciſed hearts</hi> there alledged, <hi>viz. Stealing, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Sacriledge, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 21, 22. which how well it ſuits to prove plainly, <hi>That theſe in queſtion are not regularly in the Church,</hi> let every one judge.</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.7, 9. This place ſpeaketh of <hi>bringing in the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:191784:40"/>heathen ſtrangers</hi> that were amongſt the children of Iſrael, as s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, in that it is called <hi>an Abomination</hi> ſo to do: but to <hi>bring in an Iſraelite circumciſed in fleſh, not in heart,</hi> was never counted <hi>an Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi> Again, he ſpeaketh of <hi>ſtrangers uncircumciſed in heart and fleſh,</hi> which theſe children are not. 2. Put caſe this place may by alluſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> applied to receiving of Members into the viſible Church; we agree, that none viſibly unholy ſhould be received into the Church: But our Queſtion is of ſuch <hi>as being holy, were regularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Church, and do not deſerve to be caſt out;</hi> to which caſe this place ſpeaks nothing.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee how little footing there is for our Brethrens Tenent, in theſe, or any other Scriptures they have alledged; as <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Amos</hi> 9.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. which have been conſidered in their place. And I am the more perſwaded that this <hi>Way of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> is not the <hi>Way of God,</hi> being built upon ſo manifold miſtaken and miſapplied Scriptures; whereof many of them being Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Proofs, it appears our Brethren make uſe not onely of <hi>far-fetched Conſequences,</hi> but of <hi>plain Inconſequences from the Old Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Conſequence. <hi>That to deny the Propoſition, is to break Gods Covenant, by denying the initiatory Seal to thoſe that are in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> Gen 17 9, 10, 14.</q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 1. <hi>To refuſe to Baptize one that is not regularly in Covenant, is not to break it.</hi> 2. <hi>Then it is a breach like the great Sea, to deny Communion in the Lords Supper to thoſe that have laid hold upon the Covenant, and given up themſelves to God by ſolemn Profeſſion of Faith and Repentance, which is now ſtrongly pleaded for.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. Whether theſe be not regularly in the Covenant, let the Reader judge by what is ſaid for it, and by the Scriptures alledged againſt it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To <hi>deny Communion in the Lords Supper to ſuch,</hi> is not <hi>pleaded for,</hi> much leſs <hi>ſtrongly;</hi> for, <hi>Solemn Profeſſion of Faith and Repentance</hi> is not in the Propoſition. All that is affirmed, is, That the Church-ſeed, manifeſting their continuance in the Covenant by ſuch qualifications, if they ſhall ſtill be wanting in ability to <hi>Examine themſelves, and diſcern the Lords body,</hi> may be delayed till they give ſatisfaction therein.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our Brethren in this caſe deal very hardly and partially with
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:191784:41"/>us, whil'ſt ſo oft they compare theſe with the moſt <hi>ſcandalous perſons</hi> reproved in Scripture, and with them <hi>Diſcovenanted,</hi> as they pretend: and yet at other times they lay it deeply to our charge, that we do not <hi>Receive them to the Lords Table,</hi> upon ſuch terms as are denied by them to be <hi>ſufficient to continue them in the viſible Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Arg. 4. <hi>Theſe Parents are confederate viſible Believers in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and therefore their children are to be Baptized.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>The Parents in queſtion are not ſuch, if we speak of true vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Faith, which is required</hi> Rom. 14.1. Mat. 12.20.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Be it granted, that we ſpeak of true Faith viſibly in ſome degree, yet <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1. ſpeaks rather of a perſwaſion of the <hi>lawfulneſs of eating meats unclean by the Law,</hi> as <hi>ver.</hi> 2. ſheweth.</p>
               <p>That theſe are viſible Believers <hi>in ſome degree;</hi> is thus proved:</p>
               <q>Reaſ. 1. <hi>Charity may obſerve ſundry things for it, but nothing evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent againſt it.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>This is ſaid</hi> gratis, <hi>and denied by us.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> If our Brethrens Charity could obſerve nothing for it, they might then ſhew ſomething evident againſt it, without which the Reaſon is not anſwered: for, in diſcovenanting of regular Church-members, there ought to be ſuch things evident againſt them as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Church-cenſures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>Children of the faithful, qualified but as the perſons in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, are ſaid to be Faithful,</hi> Tit. 1.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>Every one not accuſed of Riot, to be concluded to be of the Faith, is not the Apoſtles intent, nor Orthodox: Faithfulneſs is taken for Fidelity, which may be in Morall men.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Nor do the Synod ſo conclude: There is much more in the Text, then <hi>Not given to Riot,</hi> viz. 1. <hi>Children of godly Parents:</hi> 2. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated in the Faith:</hi> 3. <hi>Not ſcandalous,</hi> or <hi>Not accuſed of Riot:</hi> 4. <hi>Not unruly, but ſubject to Government:</hi> All which do ſuit well with the Propoſition. And this ſenſe of the word is given by Orthodox In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters: <hi>Marlorat</hi> Expounds the word <hi>Faithfull,</hi> of ſuch as are educated in the ſound Doctrine of Piety, and in the fear of God. <hi>Taylor,</hi> by <hi>Faithfull Children,</hi> underſtandeth ſuch as being inſtructed in the Faith, are at leaſt in external Converſation anſwerable to the Profeſſion of the Faith they make. And Reaſon would incline us
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:191784:41"/>to conceive, that the Apoſtle would require in the children of Church-Officers ſomething of Piety, as well as of Morality. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> here uſed, is frequently and commonly uſed in the New Teſtament, in the Synods ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> for <hi>Chriſtian Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> Acts 10.45. 2 Cor. 6.15. Eph 1.1. 1 Tim. 6.2. &amp; 4.3, 10, 12. &amp; 5.16.</p>
               <q>Reaſ. 3. <hi>Children of the Covenant have frequently beginnings of grace wrought in them in younger years, as Scripture-examples and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſheweth. Hence this ſort of perſons ſhewing nothing to the contrary, are in charity, or in Eccleſiaſticall reputation, viſible Believers.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>It is extraordinary to have grace in Infancy, and therefore no Rule for ordinary Church-proceedings.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. The Synod ſpeaketh not of <hi>Infancy,</hi> but of <hi>younger years,</hi> and that is not ſo extraordinary as is objected: witneſs the hopeful ſigns of grace in many that die in minority, and the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of divers, that hold forth ſeeds of grace ſown in their younget years. 2. We build not ordinary Church-proceedings immediately upon this ground; yet theſe being <hi>Church-members,</hi> we may build <hi>Church-charity</hi> upon this ground, that ſeeing <hi>ſome Church-members of this ſort</hi> have Faith in reality, <hi>all of this ſort</hi> may be ſo reputed in Church-charity: for ſo we judge of <hi>adult profeſſors</hi> in the Church; we know <hi>ſome have grace in reality,</hi> and therefore we judge ſo of <hi>all that ſort,</hi> till the contrary appear, though in the general we know <hi>Many are called, Few choſen:</hi> And what other ground have we of Church-proceedings with Church-members, but <hi>Church-charity?</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Reaſ. 4. <hi>Theſe are regularly in the Church, and therefore viſible Saints in the account of Scripture, which is the account of Truth,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.2. &amp; 14.33.</q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 1. <hi>The children in queſtion are not regularly in the Church, for then the Parents being dead, the children ſurviving ſhould make a Church, enjoy Ordinances, chuſe Officers, which is denied; and it is incredible to deny them that power when their Parents are alive, and they will not be long kept from putting it forth, though they may for a while.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. If we may thus argue, by putting caſes, that for ought appeareth, never yet hapned in the world, <hi>viz. That all the Members in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:191784:42"/>a Church ſhould be ſo taken away, that none remain but ſuch as theſe children.</hi> By like reaſon one may prove that women and children are not regularly in the Church: for, if all the men die, they ſhould <hi>make a Church, chuſe Officer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which will be denied.</hi> Yea, thus I will prove, That this or that man is not regularly in the Church; for, if all men die but one or two, they cannot <hi>make a Church,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Were the Rules of Chriſt obſerved, ſuch a caſe could not fall out: For, (as Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> anſwereth the Anabaptiſt in a caſe not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like this) <hi>Let there be a due watchfulneſs of the Church over theſe children to fit them for the Lords Table, and either the Lord, in the faithfulneſs of his Covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, will ſanctifie their hearts to prepare them for it; or elſe he will leave them to diſcover their hypocriſie and profaneneſs in the ſight of all, to prevent the pollution of his Table, and the corruption of Diſcipline.</hi> Grounds and Ends of Baptiſm, <hi>pag.</hi> 161, 163. And had we thus done, through the <hi>Bleſſing of Chriſt,</hi> which he hath promiſed upon his Ordinances, ſuch caſes could not fall out; neither had there been ſo much need or uſe of this fifth Propoſition, that is now ſo great a matter of Diſpute; and I fear this Oppoſition of the Diſſenters will increaſe our Difficulties. Neither do I ſee ſo much danger of theſe <hi>not being kept from putting forth a power to chuſe Officers, &amp;c.</hi> if they were trained up under Church-diſcipline, as in our Brethrens Way; who acknowledge them <hi>Church-members,</hi> and cannot rid their hands regularly of them, without acts of Church-diſcipline, which yet they deny to belong to their perſons immediately.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If ſuch a caſe ſhould fall out, it is not impoſſible not abſurd to ſay, That a people retaining the Eſſentials of a true Church, may fall into ſuch a degeneracy or decay, as to be unfit for Ordinances, or to thuſe Officers, untill they be further prepared by the Preaching of the Goſpel unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 2. <hi>To the Scriptures,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.2. &amp; 14.33.</q> they ſay, <hi>That by a Church of Saints primarily, the better part of Saints are underſtood, the reſt Synecdochically, though not ſo in truth, yet ſo called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> If all be <hi>ſo called, though ſome be not ſo in truth,</hi> then the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is yielded, That in Scripture &amp; Eccleſiaſtical account, all <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members</hi> are <hi>Saints:</hi> and who ſhall tell us which are ſo <hi>in truth,</hi> and which not, till impenitency in ſin gives us cauſe to count them as <hi>Heathens and Publicans?</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:191784:42"/> Reaſ. 5. <hi>Being in the Covenant, and Baptized, they have faith given them indefinitely in the Promiſe, and ſealed to them in Baptiſm,</hi> Deut. 30.6. <hi>which continueth valid, and is a valid Teſtimony for them, whil'ſt they do not reject it.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>The Promiſe is indefinite, not univerſal: whence the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be, Some circumciſed or baptized ones are Believers: But heſe in queſtion are circumciſed or baptized ones: Therefore,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or thus, The Roman Catholicks are baptized: Therefore,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> 1. I ſee our Brethren can make a falſe Syllogiſm, to decline the force of an Argument that would rightly conclude. Thus; If <hi>ſome children,</hi> being under that <hi>indefinite Promiſe,</hi> be Believers (for God is true of his Promiſe) then all ſuch children are not to be rejected as unbelievers, as our Brethren would: But ſome baptized ones be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under that <hi>indefinite Promiſe,</hi> are Believers: Therefore. Now who can ſay who are ſuch, and who are not, till they reject the grace of the Promiſe, and by impenitency in ſin are to be accounted as <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Publicans?</hi> For, though the Promiſe of <hi>Heart-circumciſion</hi> being but <hi>indefinite,</hi> is effectually performed to <hi>ſome</hi> onely, not to <hi>all;</hi> yet they are all alike to the Church, till the difference doth ſome way openly appear. 2 To apply this to the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> ſavours not of ingenuity: for are they the ſeed of <hi>Confederate viſible Believers,</hi> of whom our Diſpute is? or are they <hi>Regularly Baptized?</hi> or do they ſhew <hi>nothing to the contrary,</hi> that profeſs Popery?</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 2. <hi>It is not an indefinite Promiſe there, becauſe it is certainly made good to ſuch as return with their Souls,</hi> ver. 1, 2.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This doth not hinder the indefiniteneſs of the Promiſe, but confirmeth it. And their effectual <hi>return</hi> to God, is the fruit of that Promiſe, and <hi>indefinite</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. 3. <hi>An indefinite Promiſe doth not capacitate all children to receive the Seals.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Neither is ſo much affirmed; but this, with the other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, doth render them <hi>viſible Believers in Eccleſiaſticall repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> which is the ſcope of this fourth Argument.</p>
               <q>Arg. 5. <hi>The deniall of Baptiſm to theſe, hath a dangerous tendency to Irreligion and Apoſtacy, becauſe it denieth the children of the Church to have any part in the Lord,</hi> Joſh. 22.24, 25, 26.</q>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:191784:43"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. The Brethren deny the Conſequence, affirming, <hi>That thirty or fourty years experience in</hi> New-England, <hi>through the mercy of God, ſheweth the contrary.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This is a bare deniall, without anſwering the Reaſon from <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22. Surely that religious generation had a deeper ſenſe of that danger, and more ſolicitous care to prevent it, then they have.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When our Brethren in their Preface <hi>To the Generall Court,</hi> take notice of the <hi>Many, Great, and Prevailing Corruptions of Youth,</hi> that need Reformation by Church-diſcipline, this might abate our glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of contrary <hi>Experience for thirty or fourty years,</hi> in reſpect of the danger of <hi>Irreligion and Apoſtacy</hi> in the ſeed of the Church. But if this be ſo, it ſeemeth our Brethren do think that there are <hi>many more</hi> then <hi>A few Names in</hi> N. England, <hi>that hold faſt the Name of Chriſt, and are ſtedfaſt in the Faith and Order of the Goſpel, and do not own ſo great an Apoſtacy of Elders and People,</hi> as the Author of the Preface preſents to the World.</p>
               <q>Arg. 6. <hi>The perſons in queſtion are perſonall, immediate, and yet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuing Members of the Church, and therefore their children are to be Baptized.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Our Brethren here only ſpeak to the firſt Branch, concerning their <hi>perſonal memberſhip,</hi> having ſpoken to the third Branch before. But the ſecond Branch about their <hi>immediate memberſhip</hi> they leave untouch'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>If the meaning be, that the Promiſe to their believing Parents reacheth them, and that they are wrapped up together with them; the Aſſertion is granted, as far as concerneth the ſeed of Confederating Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in their minority: But if the meaning be, that they are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers by their own Perſonall act, then it is denied.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This diſtinction of <hi>Members wrapped up in their Parents,</hi> and <hi>Members by their own Perſonall act,</hi> is a Riddle that no Scripture doth unfold. Let us hold to Scripture-phraſes, and the meaning will be plain and eaſie, viz. <hi>They are Members in their own perſons, by the Lords actuall entring into Covenant with their perſons diſtinct from their Parents, and ſetting the Seal of the Covenant upon their perſons;</hi> as hath been proved from <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7, 9. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.10, 11.</p>
               <q>Proof 1. <hi>They are perſonally holy,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14. <hi>therefore Members in their own perſons.</hi>
               </q>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:191784:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>This concerns children in minority, or the ſeed of Believers and Members in full Communion, and therefore it reacheth them not when adult and grown.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Here our Brethren ſpeak out; <hi>That the foederal holineſs and Charch-memberſhip of the church ſeed, weareth quite out with their infancy or minority:</hi> though ſometime they ſpeak otherwiſe, as was noted upon their Conceſſion in their Anſwer to the Argument of the Synod, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. in the end. But no Scripture will prove this; yea, the whole tenour of Scripture-ſtories of the Church, convinceth the contrary. See <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.4.</p>
               <q>Proof 2. <hi>They are perſonally Baptized, the Seal of Memberſhip is applied to their own perſons, which being regularly done, is a divine teſtimony that they are in their own perſons members of the Church.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>So are the Papiſts in</hi> Rome; <hi>and are they perſonal Members? The</hi> Shechemites <hi>and</hi> Edomites <hi>were circumciſed: there is</hi> par ratio.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> This is a very ſlight evading of the Argument, which ſpeaketh of <hi>Baptiſm regularly done.</hi> I had thought our Brethren did not think Baptiſm <hi>regularly done in</hi> Rome, or Circumciſion <hi>regularly applied to the</hi> Shechemites <hi>and</hi> Edomites: Or if not, could they ſuppoſe that there is <hi>par ratio</hi> a like reaſon between <hi>Baptiſm regularly done,</hi> and <hi>not regularly done?</hi> Except they ſhould mean, that <hi>there is like reaſon between Baptiſm in</hi> Rome, <hi>and the Circumciſion of the</hi> She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemites <hi>and</hi> Edomites; and that is granted.</p>
               <q>Proof 3. <hi>They are perſonally under Diſcipline, and liable to Church-cenſures in their own perſons. See</hi> Propoſ. 3.</q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>This is granted in the ſenſe given before; yet not ſo perſonal, as to have right to all Church-priviledges, as is confeſſed by all.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> That ſenſe given before, is confuted before. 2. If they have right to all <hi>Church-priviledges</hi> properly belonging to Members as ſuch, it is ſufficient. 3. Their want of <hi>actuall enjoyment of ſome Church-priviledges,</hi> is not for want of <hi>right unto them,</hi> but for want of ſuch <hi>Qualifications</hi> as may make them fit for <hi>actuall enjoyment of them,</hi> viz. <hi>Such increaſe of Faith as is requiſite,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> well expreſſeth, it, <hi>Medul. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 32. <hi>Sect.</hi> 13.</p>
               <q>Proof 4. <hi>They are perſonally (by means of the Covenant) in a viſible ſtate of ſalvation. To ſay they are not Members in their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:191784:44"/>but in their Parents, would be as if one ſhould ſay, They are ſaved in their Parents, and not in their own perſons.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>It is granted they are in a ſtate of Salvation, and nearer the Kingdome of Heaven then Heathens are: but they are not viſibly at preſent in a ſtate of Salvation,</hi> Mark 12.34. <hi>But to infer, That if they be not Members in their own perſons, but in their Parents, then they ſhall not be ſaved in their own perſons, but in their Parents; this is utterly inconſequent: unleſs in ſhould be ſaid, that all, and onely they that are Members in their own perſons, ſhall be ſaved; which were ſad and Heterodox.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> To grant they are in <hi>a ſtate of Salvation,</hi> and yet <hi>not viſibly ſo at preſent,</hi> ſheweth that this Argument is greatly miſtaken. The ground of the Argument is this: It is the Priviledge of the Church (by Gods Covenant) to be the Redeemed and Saved People of the Lord: Chriſt is the Saviour of his Body the Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus it is with the viſible Church viſibly: And hence ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Salvation is of the Jews,</hi> Joh. 4.22. And ſo ſpeaking of the <hi>little ones,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Of ſuch is the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> Mark 10.14. And hence the Inference is alſo much miſtaken; which is this: If their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſhip (by means of the Covenant) ſetteth them in a viſible <hi>ſtate of Salvation,</hi> (as it doth, upon the grounds laid down) then, ſuppoſing <hi>this Memberſhip</hi> be in their <hi>Parents onely,</hi> and not in their <hi>own perſons,</hi> it would follow, that this <hi>viſible ſtate of Salvation</hi> is in their <hi>Parents onely,</hi> and not in their <hi>own perſons:</hi> and ſo if they be ſaved according to this Covenant, it muſt be <hi>in their Parents,</hi> and not <hi>in their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> And hereby it appeareth, how greatly this Opinion bereaveth the Parents of that hope and comfort they take in their dying Infants, by reaſon of <hi>Gods Covenant made with their ſeed.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Proof 5. <hi>When they commit iniquity, they perſonally break the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nane, and therefore they are perſonal members,</hi> Jer. 11.2, 10. Eze. 16.</q>
               <p>
                  <q>Anſ. <hi>The Covenant there spoken of is the Moral Law, as the Texts ſhew; which any man never in, or caſt out of the Church, may break.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reply.</hi> Truly this Anſwer (as the reſt) is far from ſatisfying the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of the Synod. The Texts alledged, expreſly call their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, <hi>A breaking of the Covenant:</hi> and what then if the Texts ſpeak of the <hi>Moral Law?</hi> is not the obſervation of the Moral Law a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:191784:44"/>duty of the Covenant, <hi>viz. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have God for our God, To love him, Fear him, &amp;c.?</hi> Or is the breach of the Moral Law, no breach of the Covenant in them that are in Covenant, becauſe others not in Covenant may break it? What ſenſe and reaſon is in this? When a Maſter chargeth his Apprentice with breach of his Covenant in Stealing his Maſters goods; ſhould he anſwer, It was no breach of Covenant, becauſe others that were never in Covenant, may be guilty of Stealing alſo? Would this anſwer prove it was no breach of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant? Juſt ſo is the caſe here: When the Lord chargeth the adult Members of the Church with breach of their Covenant in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral duties of the Covenant, to ſay, <hi>The Covenant there spoken of is the Moral Law, which ſuch as were never in, or caſt out of the Church, may break.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Brethren here think fit to make a ſtand; onely concluding in the words of the Presbyterian Miniſters, wherewith they would ſeem to be well ſatisfied. But the known Practice of thoſe Reverend Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that do <hi>Baptize divers Children whoſe Parents they receive not to the Lords Table,</hi> doth perſwade me, that ſuch a Profeſſion as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeribed in the fifth Propoſition, would be readily accepted of by them, as a credible Profeſſion for the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm to their ſeed, And this is the more evident to me, by that which is here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in the ſecond Paragraph, wherein they deſcribe the perſons to be Baptized, thus: <hi>Baptiſm is an holy Sacrament, in which a perſon profeſſing the Chriſtian Faith, or the Infant-ſeed of ſuch, is Baptized, &amp;c.</hi> which is fully anſwered in the fifth Propoſition.</p>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>Sixth Propoſition, which dependeth upon the Fifth,</hi> our Brethren onely declare their Diſſent.</p>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>Seventh Propoſition,</hi> they ſay, <hi>It is cautelouſly penned,</hi> and do not Object againſt it: onely deſice <hi>Care in the Application thereof, with what Churches we have Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>ſecond Queſtion,</hi> About <hi>CONSOCIATION OF CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCHES,</hi> they have declared their Conſent in all the Propoſitions laid down by the Synod, and here Object nothing.</p>
               <p>And herein I do willingly and gladly acknowledge the ingenuity of our dear Brethren; who though they be earneſt and quick ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, in ſuch things wherein they differ, yet do freely declare their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:191784:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>Conſent in other things: which giveth me the more hope, that after a fair Debate of this Queſtion, we may at length meet ſweetly in the ſame Truth, which perhaps neither of us do as yet ſo clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, as we may (through the help of Chriſt) attain unto. <hi>We know but in part, Believe in part, and Propheſie in part,</hi> and are imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in all we do; and therefore muſt wait for, and endeavour after further diſcoveries of the minde of God.</p>
               <p>And to this end (in caſe what hath been, and is here, or what ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be Publiſhed about this Queſtion, ſhould not clear up the Truth to ſatisfaction, but that further Replies ſhould be made) My earneſt Motion and Deſire is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That all Reflections upon mens Perſons, and other impertinent Diſcourſes, being laid aſide, the main iſſue of the Queſtion in Debate may be cloſely followed; which, I perceive, is come in a manner to this narrow, <hi>viz. Whether the Perſons deſcribed in the fifth Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be regularly Church-members;</hi> for this is all along denied by our Brethren, and ſeveral wayes alledged, whereby they ſhould become Non-members, as, <hi>By their Self-Excommunication, By Gods Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. My Motion and Deſire is, That the Scriptures alone, according to their true ſenſe and ſcope, may be made the Touchſtone to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Truth: Theſe <hi>are able to make the man of God fully furniſhed to every good work.</hi> I deny not the uſe of the Concurring Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the godly Learned: And it is well known how fully the advantage lieth on the Synods ſide in that reſpect; yet I ſee men are too apt to make uſe of Sentences of Authors that ſeem to favour their Opinion, though indeed contrary to the meaning and judgement of thoſe Authors: And this tends to amuſe and puzzle the common ſort of Readers, and enlarge Diſputes, but doth not tend to clear up the Truth. If theſe two things might be attended, I doubt not but this Caſe would have a ſpeedy and comfortable iſſue.</p>
               <p>Now the Lord God of Truth, Purity and Peace, direct all our hearts into the Right <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfeigned Love, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of his Holy Will in all things. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
